<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" >

<channel>
	<title>Online Map &#8211; Justin Gosses Home</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/online-map/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Geology, GIS, and CODE + Resumes</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2019 00:35:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9.11</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://i1.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/cropped-JustinGosses_logo.jpg?fit=32%2C32</url>
	<title>Online Map &#8211; Justin Gosses Home</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">102288347</site>	<item>
		<title>What do I get out of conferences?</title>
		<link>/what-do-i-get-out-of-conferences/</link>
		<comments>/what-do-i-get-out-of-conferences/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2017 06:23:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AAPG]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Agile Geoscience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conference]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[convention]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hackathon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HTML]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NASA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Map]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[python]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[talks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tutorials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=894</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Four conferences, two hackathons, and a lot of meet-ups: Analyzing what I&#8217;ve gotten from technical gatherings outside of work this year&#160; Part 1 &#8211;  The PremiseOver the last year, I&#8217;ve been lucky to attend more than my usual number of conferences, meetups, and hackathons. Some of the events were paid by work, some were paid<a href="/what-do-i-get-out-of-conferences/">[...]</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/what-do-i-get-out-of-conferences/">What do I get out of conferences?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 style="text-align: center;">Four conferences, two hackathons, and a lot of meet-ups: Analyzing what I&#8217;ve gotten from technical gatherings outside of work this year</h3><p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Part 1 &#8211;  The Premise</h2><p>Over the last year, I&#8217;ve been lucky to attend more than my usual number of conferences, meetups, and hackathons. Some of the events were paid by work, some were paid by me, and some were free. As my last event for 2017 is coming up, I&#8217;m asking myself two questions.</p><p><strong>First, what did I get out of the gatherings I attended?</strong></p><p><strong>Second, what types of events should I attend next year in order to maximize the benefits I&#8217;m interested in?</strong></p><p>As I see it, attending technical gatherings can have a range of benefits:</p>
<ol>
<li>People
<ul>
<li>Meet leaders in the field</li>
<li>Make new contacts and catch up with old contacts</li>
<li>Meet many vendors at once</li>
<li>Market yourself and your company</li>
<li>Gain a better understanding of where your skills and knowledge rank</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Skills
<ul>
<li>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</li>
<li>Learn what to do or not do from others&#8217; experiences</li>
<li>Attend a tutorial and take the first few steps in a new skill with someone there to lead you</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Knowledge of the environment beyond your immediate organization
<ul>
<li>Gain exposure to a wide range of tools, methods, and applications</li>
<li>Learn what is upcoming and new</li>
<li>Understand how the larger market or community is evolving</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol><p>Working under the assumption that understanding what I got out of the past events will help me plan ahead, I&#8217;ve compiled a description of various technical gatherings I&#8217;ve attended over the last twelve months.</p>
<h2>Part 2 &#8211; The Data</h2><p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;">AAPG ACE 2017</h2>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">What is it?</span></h5><p><a href="http://www.aapg.org/">American Association of Petroleum Geologist</a>s Annual <a href="http://ace.aapg.org/2017/about">Conference & Exhibit</a>. It is the main conference for petroleum geologists and the largest of several AAPG conferences. The conference can cost between $65 and $650 depending on whether you are a student and when you purchase.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>Geologists in the oil and gas industry and some geophysicists. Engineers have their own conferences. The focus is on technical aspects as opposed to business environment or deal making.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>Most people dress like they do at work, which is to say dress pants, dress pants, and collared shirts if you&#8217;re a guy or the equivalent if female. If you&#8217;re presenting or looking for work, you might wear a suit and tie. A few people wear jeans. There are no funny t-shirts.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p>This year it was in Houston. The conference moves every year between North American oil industry centers like Houston, Long Beach, Calgary, and Denver.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p>The average over the last 5 years has been <a href="http://www.aapg.org/events/conferences/ace">6,900</a>.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>Most of the talks follow the pattern of a typical science talk explaining what they did in very rough terms and what their conclusions are.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Make new contacts and catch up with old contacts</em>
<ul>
<li>AAPG ACE was very good for making connections with people I haven&#8217;t seen in a while now that I&#8217;m out of the oil and gas industry.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Learn what is upcoming and new</em>
<ul>
<li>It is also a great place for seeing what is at the forefront of the intersection between industry and academia in geology as various research consortia present talks and posters.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Benefit areas that were lacking</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</em></li>
<li><em>Attend a tutorial and take the first few steps in a new skill with someone to lead you</em>
<ul>
<li>Compared with tech conferences, the range of talk types is limited. There are almost no &#8220;how to&#8221; or &#8220;when to use blank method&#8221; talks. Everything is in the science talk mold.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>AAPG was great for catching up with people and getting a peek at what other people are working on, even if it is a small peak. Some of the talks can be frustratingly vague due to intellectual property constraints. Field trips provide some opportunity for improving technical skills, but they typically cost enough that you&#8217;ll only attend if your employer is paying. The main convention talks tend to focus on what someone has been done rather than what you could do.</p><p>If you&#8217;re interested in hearing more about what geology conferences are missing and what they might be able to learn from certain tech conference models, the Undersampled Radio podcast recent had a great conversation on this topic starting at 30 minutes into <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vCeNA9btD9E"> episode 46</a>.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;">SXSW Interactive</h2>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;"> What is it?</span></h5><p>South by Southwest is a mega-conference in which the &#8220;<a href="https://www.sxsw.com/festivals/interactive/">Interactive</a>&#8221; sub-conference focuses on digital, internet, intelligent future, social impact, journalism, start-ups, AR/VR, music industry, sports industry, and the workplace. The interactive sub-conference takes place over 5 days and overlaps with the education, music, film, and comedy sub-conferences. More information <a href="https://www.sxsw.com/festivals/interactive/">here</a>. SXSW Interactive tickets cost $1,225.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>Marketing companies, hip people, students who volunteer to get their otherwise expensive tickets paid for, and people in the digital space who want to see what is new or make connections.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>Varies from nerdy t-shirts to professor jackets with elbow patches. If business casual, a little on the fashionable side.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p>Austin, every year.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_by_Southwest">30,621</a></p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>The talks here range from &#8220;this is new&#8221; to &#8220;we did and you can too&#8221; to &#8220;let&#8217;s talk about the context of something&#8221; to &#8220;fluff and buzzwords&#8221;.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Meet leaders in the field</em>
<ul>
<li>I talked with <a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~jheer/">Vint Cerf</a>, one of the &#8220;fathers of the internet, and <a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~jheer/">Jeffrey Heer </a>, a professor who has had a role in many key data visualization code libraries, such as <a href="https://vega.github.io/vega/">vega.js</a>, <a href="https://vincent.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">vincent.py</a>, and <a href="https://d3js.org/">d3.js</a>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Understand trends in the larger market or community. Learn what is new</em></li>
<li><em>Learn what is upcoming and new</em>
<ul>
<li>Saw a lot in regards to VR/AR that was cutting edge.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Understand how the larger market or community is evolving</em></li>
<li><em>Meet many vendors at once</em>
<ul>
<li>Largest exhibit showroom of any conference in this list.</li>
<li>Met with two vendors afterward and used the experience to benchmark against other vendors post conference</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet people doing similar work and learn from their experiences</em>
<ul>
<li>There were several talks that inspired ideas for future projects based on what similar teams had done in other organizations. Post-talk discussions were great for identifying failures to avoid in upcoming projects.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Benefit areas that were lacking</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</em>
<ul>
<li>Talks tend to lack technical depth.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Attend a tutorial and take the first few steps in a new skill with someone to lead you</em>
<ul>
<li>There weren&#8217;t any tutorials.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li>There are more talks about products and solutions than methods or tools.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>There were some great talks that inspired potential future projects, but meeting people was the more valuable activity at SXSW. Perhaps for that reason, there were <a href="http://schedule.sxsw.com/2017/03/10/events/conference/Interactive/type/panel">several time slots</a> for people to just &#8220;meet-up&#8221; in a room and talk about a specific topic.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">PyCon2017</h3>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">What is it?</span></h5><p><a href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/">PyCon</a> is the largest conference for Python developers. Web development and data analytics are the two focus areas. The base convention ticket for PyCon is $600 for corporate, $350 for individuals, and $125 for students. If sign-up for the max amount of tutorials, total ticket price can be up to $1200.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>People who write code in Python. The male/female ratio at PyCon was maybe 70/30, which made it the most unbalanced of all the conferences.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>There&#8217;s a range, but, compared to the other conferences, it was high on nerdy t-shirts and low on formal or business clothes.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p>PyCon was held in Portland, Oregon. PyCon holds their conferences in the same city for two years before switching, which minimizes costs and planning requirements. Next year, it will be in Cleveland, Ohio. Previous to Portland, it was in Montreal.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Python_Conference">3,391</a> badges were picked up from registration.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>PyCon is split into two days of tutorials, three days of talks, and then four days of open-source development sprints.</p>
<ul>
<li>Tutorials are half a day in length. Topics included Bayesian machine learning, time series analysis, network analysis, using flask for microservices, <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/schedule/tutorials/">etc</a>.</li>
<li>During the main convention, talks ranged in style from:
<ul>
<li>We did this with Python</li>
<li>Best practice in some aspect of writing code</li>
<li>The &#8220;craft&#8221; of some part of writing python code</li>
<li>Introduction to a new python module or open-source project</li>
<li>Introduction to some activity that can be done with python</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>During the sprints, open-source Python <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/community/sprints/">projects</a> are built or extended.</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Meet leaders in the field</em>
<ul>
<li>Ended up at a bar with <a href="https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/the-birth-and-death-of-javascript">Gary Bernhardt</a> , who runs &#8220;destroyallsoftware.com&#8221;, and <a href="https://www.kennethreitz.org/projects/">Kenneth Reitz</a>, the main author of the &#8220;requests&#8221; python module.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Attend a tutorial and take the first few steps in a new skill with someone to lead you</em>
<ul>
<li>Attended excellent half-day <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/schedule/tutorials/">tutorials</a> on Bayesian machine learning, time series analysis, and MQTT protocol.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</em>
<ul>
<li>Several talks were on the &#8220;craft&#8221; of some aspect of writing code, examples included documentation, testing, and sever reliability.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet people doing similar work and learn from their experiences</em>
<ul>
<li>Talked to a variety of people doing similar work in different organizations and learned how their teams and approaches differ from mine.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li>Got exposure to a range of new modules and methods and what they could be used for.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Benefit areas that were lacking</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Meet many vendors at once</em>
<ul>
<li>Although there was an exhibit floor, the number and diversity of vendors were a bit lacking for a conference of that size.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>PyCon was excellent for picking up bits of new skills and improving my understanding of what python modules I might be able to use in future projects. Many of the talks had a focus on leaving the audience with something useful, which made it a great conference for learning. My <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zm0x1uLg-SKGI4nbu-_ND_44Bycl_wo4tTxVpjDDC6g/edit?usp=sharing">notes</a> have links to the slides and Jupyter Notebooks used by some of the presenters.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">Johnson Space Center Data Science Day</h3>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">What is it?</span></h5><p><a href="https://fal.jsc.nasa.gov/DSD/">Data Science Day 2.0</a> was two days of talks around various aspects of data science, data visualization, and analytics. It was free to attend.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>A mixture of NASA civil servants, NASA contractors, vendors, and the public who were interested in the subject matter.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>Mostly business casual with some suits and ties.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p>Gilruth Center just outside Johnson Space Center, Houston, Texas.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p>I estimate 200-350.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>Talks ranged from programming newbie talks to &#8220;we built this&#8221; talks to &#8220;this capability exists&#8221; talks.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li>Got exposure to skills and methods I haven&#8217;t used myself yet.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet people doing similar work and learn from their experiences</em>
<ul>
<li>Made connections to others at Johnson Space Center who were interested in working with our team.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Market yourself and your company</em>
<ul>
<li>Presented a <a href="http://slides.com/justingosses/history_data_visualization_tools#/">talk</a> on the history of digital data visualization tools.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Benefit areas that were lacking</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</em>
<ul>
<li>There weren&#8217;t many talks about the craft of data science or data visualization.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>Given Johnson Space Center is a rather spread out campus with many buildings, events like this are really valuable for communicating about skills that cross normal organizational boundaries. Attending an event of this type wouldn&#8217;t replace something like PyCon, however, due to the lack of tutorials and in-depth skill sessions.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">Various Houston Tech Meetups</h3>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">What is it?</span></h5><p>There are a variety of <a href="https://www.meetup.com/find/?allMeetups=false&keywords=tech&radius=25&userFreeform=Houston%2C+TX&mcId=c77001&mcName=Houston%2C+TX&sort=default">meetups</a> in Houston that focus on t<a href="https://www.meetup.com/Collabonauts/">ech</a>, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/houston-js/events/240279389/">web development</a>, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Houston-VR-Developers/events/239502556/">virtual reality</a>, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Hackster-Hardware-Meetup-Houston/events/240263187/">IoT</a>, and <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Houston-Energy-Data-Science-Meetup/">data science</a>. These are typically 1.5 to 4-hour meetings around various topics held every month or two somewhere in Houston. I regularly go to ones on <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Houston-Data-Visualization-Meetup/">data visualization</a>, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/houston-js/">JavaScript</a>, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/python-web-houston/">Python</a>, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sketchcity/events/239311484/">civic projects</a>, and <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Houston-React-Js-Group/events/240297939/">front-end web development</a>. They are free to attend although sometimes donations are requested for snacks.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>Anyone interested in the subject. Attendees range from complete newbies to professional developers.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>Casual to whatever people were wearing at work.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p>It varies from civic community spaces to tech companies to coffee shops and bars.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p>5-75, but many times a year.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>The two most common types are &#8220;introduction to blank&#8221; talks and &#8220;this is what I have done with blank&#8221; talks. My favorite is Houston data visualization meetup&#8217;s monthly &#8220;data jams&#8221;. A cleaned dataset is provided. Participants have 4 hours to build data visualizations with any code library or software tool they care to apply. This is a great way to learn about new tools and methods for data visualization.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li>You&#8217;ll get exposure to a wide range of tools and approaches for a single topic.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet people doing similar work and learn from their experiences</em>
<ul>
<li>Make connections across industries and organizations in Houston.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Make new contacts and catch up with old contacts</li>
<li><em>Market yourself and your company</em>
<ul>
<li>The easiest place to present a talk or contribute to the local developer community.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Benefit areas that were lacking</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Meet many vendors at once</em>
<ul>
<li>Vendor pitches are generally frowned upon, so there aren&#8217;t that many. Energy industry meetups are the exception.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet leaders in the field</em>
<ul>
<li>Unfortunately, Houston is not much of a tech hub, so there aren&#8217;t that many big names here.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>The main benefit of meetups for me is the exposure to a wide range of tools applied to the same topic or problem. This saves me a great amount of time in terms of researching and comparing new tools myself.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">Space-Apps Challenge Houston</h3>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">What is it?</span></h5><p>A <a href="https://2017.spaceappschallenge.org/">global hackathon</a> that uses NASA data, but is hosted locally in many cities around the world. This was the first year the event was hosted in Houston for several years. Participants form teams and have two days to hack together a solution, usually a web application but sometimes hardware, to one of the NASA <a href="https://2017.spaceappschallenge.org/challenges/">challenges</a>. It is free to attend. There was sponsor swag, coffee, beer, and food from <a href="http://stationhouston.com/">Station Houston</a>, Amazon Web Services, Intel, and <a href="https://www.yelp.com/biz/morningstar-houston">Morningstar Coffee</a>. I was a technical mentor during the event, not a participant.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>Participants at the Houston event included high school students with a little coding knowledge, recent coding boot camp graduates, computer science undergraduates, IBM engineers, and professional web developers.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>85% jeans & t-shirt and 15% slightly fancier.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p><a href="https://www.theironyard.com/locations/houston">The Iron Yard</a>, a coding boot camp with locations in various cities, including Houston.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p>~30</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>Aside from a 20-minute talk on NASA civilian science, the time was spent working on each team&#8217;s project. You can read more about some of the projects created at the Houston event <a href="https://2017.spaceappschallenge.org/locations/houston/">here</a>.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li>Two of the teams used technologies I hadn&#8217;t worked with before.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</em></li>
<li><em>Make new contacts and catch up with old contacts</em>
<ul>
<li>Made connections with several or the participants</li>
<li>Worked with <a href="http://stationhouston.com/">Station</a>, <a href="https://www.theironyard.com/locations/houston">The Iron Yard</a>, and several <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Houston-Data-Visualization-Meetup/">meet-up group</a> leads to organize the event.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Benefit areas that were lacking</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Meet leaders in the field</em></li>
<li><em>Meet people doing similar work and learn from their experiences</em></li>
<li><em>Meet many vendors at once</em></li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>As a participant, hackathons are great for taking a method or technology that is new to you, cramming as much about it into your brain as possible, and then applying it in a very intense, short period of time. As a technical mentor, who also did a bit of event organization, it is a great way to expand your network, learn from others, and you get some of the previously mentioned technical benefits too.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">Agile Scientific Paris Subsurface Hackathon</h3>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">What is it?</span></h5><p>A hackathon associated with a geological society conference in Paris.  This is one of <a href="https://agilescientific.com/">Agile Scientific&#8217;s</a> hackathons that take place 1-3 times a year at geology and geophysics conferences. Total is co-organizing it. It is free to attend.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>Geologists and geophysicists who know how to code, usually in Python. Web development skills are typically sparse. Several people, including myself, will be participating as &#8220;robots&#8221;. This means I&#8217;ll be teleconferencing into the hackathon and my face will be appearing on a little laptop there.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>Most of the on-location participants will be French, so I&#8217;m assuming they will likely be better dressed than me.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p>Virtual & Paris.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p>Not sure as it hasn&#8217;t happened yet, but looks to be around 50.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>There will likely be an introduction talk and then lots of coding.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li>This always seems to happen at hackathons.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;
<ul>
<li>A lot of my coding ability was picked up after I left oil and gas, so it will be nice to work with geological datasets.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Make new contacts and catch up with old contacts
<ul>
<li>Several of the participants are people I know from a previous hackathon.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>I&#8217;m hoping to use this as an opportunity to apply a new skill area that I&#8217;ll be using at work eventually but haven&#8217;t had much opportunity to use yet. Possibilities include time-series analysis, deep-learning, web-scraping, and natural language processing.</p>
<h2>Part 3  &#8211;  The Analysis</h2>
<h3>Ranking of which events had which benefits the most</h3><p>Based on the notes above, I&#8217;ve ranked the events in terms of how well they fulfilled each benefit in my list. The event that most fulfilled each benefit is in <span style="color: #ff0000;">red<span style="color: #000000;">, with second in</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">purple</span><span style="color: #000000;">, etc</span></span>.</p>
<ol>
<li>People
<ul>
<li><em>Meet leaders in the field</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">SXSW &</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">PyCon</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet people doing similar work and learn from their experiences</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff6600;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Meet-ups</span>,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">PyCon</span><span style="color: #ff9900;"><span style="color: #cc99ff;">,</span> <span style="color: #99cc00;">JSC Data Science Day<span style="color: #99ccff;">,</span></span><span style="color: #99ccff;"> and meetups</span></span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Make new contacts and catch up with old contacts</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">AAPG,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">meetups,</span> <span style="color: #99cc00;">and PyCon</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet many vendors at once</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">SXSW <span style="color: #cc99ff;">and</span></span><span style="color: #cc99ff;"> AAPG</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Market yourself and your company</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #ff0000;">SXSW,</span><span style="color: #cc99ff;"> PyCON,</span><span style="color: #993300;"> </span><span style="color: #ff9900;"><span style="color: #99cc00;">AAPG,</span> <span style="color: #99ccff;">and meetups</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Gain a better understanding of where your skills and knowledge rank</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">PyCon,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">hackathons, </span><span style="color: #99cc00;">and meetups</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Skills
<ul>
<li><em>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff6600;"><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Hackathons,</span><span style="color: #cc99ff;"> PyCon,</span></span></span> <span style="color: #99cc00;">meet-ups</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Learn what to do or not do from others&#8217; experiences</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">PyCon,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">meet-ups, </span><span style="color: #99cc00;">JSC Data Science Day</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Attend a tutorial and take the first few steps in a new skill with someone to lead you</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">PyCon,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">meet-ups, </span><span style="color: #99cc00;">hackathon</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Knowledge of the environment beyond your immediate organization
<ul>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">PyCon,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">meet-ups, </span><span style="color: #99cc00;">JSC Data Science Day,</span><span style="color: #99ccff;"> SXSW</span><br />
</span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Understand trends in the larger market or community</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">SXSW,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">meet-ups,</span> <span style="color: #99cc00;">PyCon</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Learn what is new</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;"><span style="color: #ff6600;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">PyCon,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">SXSW,</span></span></span> <span style="color: #99cc00;">JSC Data Science Day</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h3>Discussion</h3><p>Some types of events I might not want to go to every year. Other types of events I would go every year, but I might trade one conference for another with a similar style but different focus area.</p>
<h5>SXSW Interactive or another large conference of this type</h5><p>SXSW Interactive is great for getting a wide view of what is new and upcoming, but I&#8217;m not sure I need to go to it, or a conference like it, more than once every two to three years, even on a team that is responsible for keeping up with what is new.</p>
<h5>AAPG or another large science or professional association conference</h5><p>AAPG is great in terms of what it tries to be, a science conference for oil and gas geologists, but there are definitely <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vCeNA9btD9E">some aspects</a> of tech and computer language specific conferences that science and industry conferences could learn from. In-depth half-day tutorials, how-to sessions, and skill-building activities are all things that could be done in that conference space but just aren&#8217;t. A similar conference to this one, but in a computer science domain, would be <a href="https://www.ieee.org/conferences_events/index.html">IEEE</a>.</p>
<h5>PyCon or similar tech conference</h5><p>PyCon had a wide range of benefits, including tutorials and &#8220;how to do this activity well&#8221; talks that are not always present at other technical gatherings. The year before I went to <a href="https://pydata.org/chicago2016/">PyData in Chicago</a>, which, although a smaller conference, had a similar range of talks. A conference that might be similar but with a different focus is <a href="https://scipy2017.scipy.org/ehome/index.php?eventid=220975&">SciPy</a>.</p>
<h5>Hackathons</h5><p>They are great at both putting you in contact with the local developer community and showing you the range of approaching to a topic. However, they are intense. I participate or help out with 1-2 a year. More than that might be too much. I&#8217;ll do Space-Apps Houston again as there is definitely some value there both to me and to the community. Also, it is Houston! It was embarrassing there were several years when over a hundred Space-Apps hackathon events occurred globally, but there wasn&#8217;t an event in Houston. An alternative option that I seem to always be out of town for is the <a href="http://houstonhackathon.com/">Houston Hackathon</a>.</p>
<h5>Johnson Space Center Data Science Day or similar 1-2 day, &lt;300 people,  local event.</h5><p>Johnson Space Center Data Science Day is useful for making local and NASA specific people connections and seeing what others are working on, however, it can&#8217;t replace something like PyCon or PyData for learning new skills. I&#8217;ll attend and present, but I don&#8217;t really count it as a learning opportunity in the same way. Similar type one to two-day speaker events are held at Rice University focusing on big data and <a href="http://ml2017.rice.edu/">machine learning</a>.</p>
<h5>Houston tech meetups</h5><p>Tech meet-ups are my bread and butter learning opportunity. The combination of free, relatively easy to fit in your schedule as you don&#8217;t have to take days off, and leading directly into side projects works out well for me, especially as someone relatively new to writing code for a living. How many meetups I attend will depend on my schedule and number of side projects, which is difficult to predict in advance.</p>
<h3>Next year plans</h3>
<h5><em>Attend 0-1</em></h5><p>AAPG and SXSW style conferences have value but a more narrow range of benefits that ranks secondary to me right now. If options for travel and training are limited, I would focus my budget elsewhere next year.</p>
<h5><em>Attend many, present at 1+, and organize at least 1</em></h5><p>Tech meetups and hackathons are great in that they&#8217;re free, local, and there&#8217;s something you could attend multiple times a week if you wanted, at least in a major US city. That frequency also represents a burn-out danger, however, so I&#8217;ll probably attend the same amount or shift to attending a little less next year.</p>
<h5><em>Attend 1+ and present at 1+</em></h5><p>JSC Data Science Day is a great way to make local connections in a large and spread out organization, but I wouldn&#8217;t consider it a replacement for training or a major conference.</p>
<h5><em>Attend 1 (consider presenting)</em></h5><p>PyCon and similar-type conferences probably offer the most value of the options examined due to the presence of many tutorials and &#8220;craft of coding&#8221; talks. My top focus for planning which conference to attend next year will be on finding a good PyCon-style conference that covers slightly different terrain but is still very applicable to work.</p>
<h3>Conclusion</h3><p>Different outside of work technical gatherings have different benefits. An exercise like this helps organize experiences into data that is easier to analyze. My conclusions on what types of conferences are the most useful for me this year and next reflects what benefits I value the most right now. My main focus is on building skills and learning new tools, which shows up in my future conference preferences.</p><p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/what-do-i-get-out-of-conferences/">What do I get out of conferences?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/what-do-i-get-out-of-conferences/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">894</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Flow Chart for Picking the Right Mapping Tool</title>
		<link>/flow-chart-for-picking-the-right-mapping-tool/</link>
		<comments>/flow-chart-for-picking-the-right-mapping-tool/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2016 19:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ArcGIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CartoDB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data visualization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[draw.io]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[flowcharts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[javascript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Javascript library]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[leaflet.js]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mapbox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Map]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Mapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Opinion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[python]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=732</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>I did some research on different tools for creating flow charts today.Originally, I started down this path trying to figure out what open-source project I might be able to hack on and produce a project that would generate XKCD style flow charts, similar to how bokeh (python library) has XCKD style plots as built-in option. I<a href="/flow-chart-for-picking-the-right-mapping-tool/">[...]</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/flow-chart-for-picking-the-right-mapping-tool/">Flow Chart for Picking the Right Mapping Tool</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I did some research on different tools for creating flow charts today.</p><p>Originally, I started down this path trying to figure out what open-source project I might be able to hack on and produce a project that would generate XKCD style flow charts, similar to how bokeh (python library) has XCKD style plots as built-in option. I was also playing around with the notion of crowd-sourced flow charts to help pick among tools and libraries as the number of options explode.</p><p>Then I got distracted and made the flow-chart below. I&#8217;ll just leave it here. It was made with <a href="http://draw.io/">draw.io</a></p><p>&nbsp;</p>
<div id="wrapper" style="width: 100%; height: 100%; overflow: scroll !important; -webkit-overflow-scrolling: touch;">
<iframe src="http://www.justingosses.com/FlowChart_MakeMaps/" width="100%" height="1200px"></iframe>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/flow-chart-for-picking-the-right-mapping-tool/">Flow Chart for Picking the Right Mapping Tool</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/flow-chart-for-picking-the-right-mapping-tool/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">732</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>ISS Fly Over</title>
		<link>/issflyover/</link>
		<comments>/issflyover/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2016 05:23:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Front-End]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ISS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[javascript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Javascript library]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[leaflet.js]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NASA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Map]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=530</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>ISS = International Space StationEarlier this week someone came into my office at work and asked to borrow three of our beanbags, so they could have recently returned astronauts sit in them while doing a facebook live-stream event. Apparently, it has become tradition. That prompted me to google ISS fly over application. I heard NASA<a href="/issflyover/">[...]</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/issflyover/">ISS Fly Over</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>ISS = International Space Station</em></p><p>Earlier this week someone came into my office at work and asked to borrow three of our beanbags, so they could have recently returned astronauts sit in them while doing a facebook live-stream event. Apparently, it has become tradition. That prompted me to google ISS fly over application. I heard NASA had put out the code that runs their &#8220;check when the International Space Station will be in view from your location&#8221; webpage. Unfortunately, my impression wasn&#8217;t quite correct. What was provided wasn&#8217;t the code for their webpage or the application that does the calculations but merely an embed code snippet that lets you put an iframe in your own webpage to theirs. Basically, it is a well-built window from this webpage into their webpage.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;div</span> <span style="color: #008000;">style=&#8221;display: inline-block; border: 1px solid #CCC; border-radius: 6px; -webkit-border-radius: 6px; -o-border-radius: 6px; position: relative; overflow: hidden; width: 310px; height: 450px;</span>&#8220;<span style="color: #ff6600;">&gt;<br />
&lt;iframe</span> <span style="color: #ff6600;">src=</span>&#8220;<span style="color: #800080;">https://spotthestation.nasa.gov/widget/widget.cfm?country=United_States&amp;region=Texas&amp;city=Houston</span>&#8221; <span style="color: #008000;">width=&#8221;310&#8243; height=&#8221;450&#8243; frameborder=&#8221;0&#8243;</span>&gt;<span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;/iframe&gt&lt/div&gt;</span></p></blockquote><p><span style="color: #ff6600;">Orange</span> = HTML, the pieces that make up the webpage. Boxes inside boxes with rules about where those boxes sit and their properties.</p><p><span style="color: #800080;">Purple</span> = URL, or address the browser goes to in order to ask politely for the NASA data to build the little ISS flyover screen.</p><p><span style="color: #008000;">Green</span> = CSS, the style rules.</p>
<div style="display: block; margin: 0 auto; text-align: center; border: 1px solid #CCC; border-radius: 6px; -webkit-border-radius: 6px; -o-border-radius: 6px; position: relative; overflow: hidden; width: 310px; height: 450px;"><iframe src="https://spotthestation.nasa.gov/widget/widget.cfm?country=United_States&region=Texas&city=Houston" width="310" height="450" frameborder="0"></iframe></div><p>&nbsp;</p>
<div><p>After googling around a bit, I found a different ISS flyover resource called <a href="http://open-notify.org/">OpenNotify</a>. Born from a hackathon, by <a href="mailto:nathan@open-notify.org">Nathan Bergey</a>, this site provides latitude and longitude, next station pass for your location, and the number of people in space. Instead of using an iframe, it uses an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Application_programming_interface">API</a>. This means, instead of being a window to another webpage like the iframe method, your webpage is sending a question to another server that responds with some information.</p>
</div><p>For example, we can get second by second updates on the lat and long of the International Space Station below.</p>
<p style="text-align: center; background-color: lightgray;">The ISS is currently over <span id="isslat">?</span>° N, <span id="isslon">?</span>° E</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The line above is generated using the following code:</p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;p</span> <span style="color: #008000;">style=&#8221;text-align: center;&#8221;</span><span style="color: #ff6600;">&gt;</span>The ISS is currently over <span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;span id=&#8221;isslat&#8221;&gt;</span>?<span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;/span&gt;</span>° N, <span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;span id=&#8221;isslon&#8221;&gt;</span>?<span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;/span&gt;</span>° E<span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;/p&gt;</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;script src=&#8221;<span style="color: #800080;">https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.12.2/jquery.min.js</span>&#8220;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;script&gt;</span><br />
<span style="color: #3366ff;">     function getISS () { $.getJSON(&#8216;</span><span style="color: #800080;">http://api.open-notify.org/iss-now.json?callback=?&#8217;, </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #800080;"><span style="color: #3366ff;">          function(data) { var lat = data[&#8216;iss_position&#8217;][&#8216;latitude&#8217;]; var lon = data[&#8216;iss_position&#8217;][&#8216;longitude&#8217;];</span></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #3366ff;">                    $(&#8216;#isslat&#8217;).html(Math.round(lat*1000)/1000.0); $(&#8216;#isslon&#8217;).html(Math.round(lon*1000)/1000.0); </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #3366ff;">          });</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #3366ff;">     setTimeout(getISS, 3000); } </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #3366ff;">     getISS();</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;/script&gt;</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">Similarly to the first code block, there is html (<span style="color: #ff6600;">orange</span>), an URL (<span style="color: #800080;">purple</span>), and CSS (<span style="color: #008000;">green</span>). What is different is between the second pair of &lt;&gt;opening and &lt;/&gt;closing orange &lt;script&gt; tags we also have some <span style="color: #3366ff;">JavaScript code in blue</span>. JavasScript is the computer language that runs in your browser. You may or may not have python or some other language installed on your computer (perhaps as a default install by the company you bought it from), but any computer with a browser can run JavaScript. This particular JavaScript script does three things.</p>
<ul>
<li style="text-align: left;">First, &#8220;<span style="color: #3366ff;"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">function getISS ()</span></span>&#8221;  establishes the name of the function, &#8220;<span style="color: #3366ff;">getISS</span>&#8220;. What is between the <span style="color: #3366ff;">{ }</span> directly after <span style="color: #3366ff;">function getISS ()</span> is the code that runs when the function is called. In the last blue line, the function name <span style="color: #3366ff;">getISS()</span> is called and the function executes.</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">Next, inside the getISS function is <span style="color: #3366ff;">$.getJSON</span>. The $ sign tells a library called Jquery to run. Jquery was previously downloaded to run locally using <span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;script src=&#8221;<span style="color: #800080;">https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.12.2/jquery.min.js</span>&#8220;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;<span style="color: #000000;">. <span style="color: #333333;">Jquery knows that </span><span style="color: #3366ff;">$.getJSON</span> <span style="color: #333333;">means to send a request to the following</span> <span style="color: #800080;">URL in purple</span> <span style="color: #333333;">and expect to get JSON formatted data back from that server. </span></span></span></li>
<li style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #ff6600;"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="color: #333333;">The next JavaScript function in blue (<span style="color: #800080;"><span style="color: #3366ff;">function(data) { var lat = data[&#8216;iss_position&#8217;][&#8216;latitude&#8217;]; var lon = data[&#8216;iss_position&#8217;][&#8216;longitude&#8217;];</span></span> ) takes that JSON data, labeled here as &#8220;<span style="color: #3366ff;">data</span>&#8220;, pulls out the parts representing lat and long and turns them into variables we can use later in the code. </span></span></span></li>
<li style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #ff6600;"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="color: #333333;">Those two variables are referred to in the next bit of JavaScript (<span style="color: #3366ff;">$(&#8216;#isslat&#8217;).html(Math.round(lat*1000)/1000.0); $(&#8216;#isslon&#8217;).html(Math.round(lon*1000)/1000.0); }); <span style="color: #333333;">) where the variables are changed into easier to read format using some math and then switched out in place of for the &#8220;<span style="color: #ff6600;">?</span>&#8221; in the following HTML (<span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;span id=&#8221;isslat&#8221;&gt;</span>?<span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;/span&gt;</span>° N, <span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;span id=&#8221;isslon&#8221;&gt;</span>?<span style="color: #ff6600;">&lt;/span&gt;</span>) the script knows where to put them as the <span style="color: #3366ff;">#</span> in the script is equivalent to the <span style="color: #ff6600;">id=</span> in html. </span></span></span></span></span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: left;">Leaflet.js</h3><p>Regenerating lat and long as digits is kinda boring though, so we&#8217;re going to put those on a map so we can see exactly where the ISS is over right now. We&#8217;re also going to have the map add a new marker every three seconds to get an idea just how fast the ISS is moving. We&#8217;re going to do this with another JavaScript library called <a href="http://leafletjs.com/">leaflet.js</a>.</p><p>Here it is at a large scale. Note, it initially takes three to five seconds for the first ISS lat and long position to load to the map. If you zoom in, you can more clearly see the ISS moving. If you leave it up for a while, you&#8217;ll get a line of markers stringing across the globe, which gives you a good idea how fast 17,150 miles per hour or slightly more than 5 miles a second actually is. The Space Station orbits Earth once every 92 minutes.</p>
<div><iframe src="http://www.justingosses.com/ISSflyOver/" width="600" height="300" frameborder="0" seamless="seamless">Browser not compatible.</iframe></div>
<div id="mapidC" class="maps center"></div><p><script src="http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet/v0.7.7/leaflet.js"></script><script src="https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.12.2/jquery.min.js"></script></p><p><script>// <![CDATA[
var map_1 = {"issLat":0,"issLong":0}
var ISSmarkers = [];


function getISS () {
		    $.getJSON('http://api.open-notify.org/iss-now.json?callback=?', function(data) {
		        var lat = data['iss_position']['latitude'];
		        var lon = data['iss_position']['longitude'];
		        $('#isslat').html(Math.round(lat*1000)/1000.0);
		        $('#isslon').html(Math.round(lon*1000)/1000.0);

		        window.map_1["issLat"]=(Math.round(lat*1000)/1000.0);
		        window.map_1["issLong"]=(Math.round(lon*1000)/1000.0)
		        console.log("ISSmarkers = ",ISSmarkers)

		    });
    	setTimeout(getISS, 3000); 
		}
		getISS();

var mymap = L.map('mapid').setView([map_1["issLat"], map_1["issLong"]], 3);

			L.tileLayer('https://api.mapbox.com/styles/v1/mapbox/satellite-v9/tiles/256/{z}/{x}/{y}?access_token={accessToken}',
			{
		    attribution: 'Map data &copy; <a href="http://openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</a> contributors, <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">CC-BY-SA</a>, Imagery © <a href="http://mapbox.com/">Mapbox</a>',
		    maxZoom: 20,
		    level: 20,
		    id: 'jgosses',
		    accessToken: 'pk.eyJ1Ijoiamdvc3NlcyIsImEiOiJjaWk2aWhua2kwMWxidDBrZndhbHBraTd1In0.IIT7dwztvQhH9ZsiOLmnMg'
		}).addTo(mymap);

var marker = L.marker([map_1["issLat"], map_1["issLong"]]).addTo(mymap);
// ]]&gt;</script></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/issflyover/">ISS Fly Over</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/issflyover/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">530</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Data Visualization Compilations</title>
		<link>/data-visualization-compilations/</link>
		<comments>/data-visualization-compilations/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2016 04:40:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CartoDB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CSS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Front-End]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HTML]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[javascript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mapbox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Map]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Mapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=453</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>A Compilation of Data Visualization Compilations:There are a wide variety of tools out there for data visualization. Some nice people have come up with compilations of their favorite tools. Other people have created galleries of really outstanding data visualizations that you can use as inspiration. Over the past year, I&#8217;ve bookmarked a lot of them.<a href="/data-visualization-compilations/">[...]</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/data-visualization-compilations/">Data Visualization Compilations</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>A Compilation of Data Visualization Compilations:</h3><p>There are a wide variety of tools out there for data visualization. Some nice people have come up with compilations of their favorite tools. Other people have created galleries of really outstanding data visualizations that you can use as inspiration. Over the past year, I&#8217;ve bookmarked a lot of them. This post is a curated compilation of compilations. If you&#8217;re interested in learning about data visualization on the web, this post might save you some time digging around the internet. Alternatively, it might be a massive time sink.</p>
<h3>Catalog of Data Visualization Types:</h3>
<h4><a href="http://www.datavizcatalogue.com/" target="_blank">Dataviz Catalogue</a></h4><p>This is a great site for thinking about, or discussing with others, the various advantages and disadvantages of different data visualization styles. Not sure what data visualization style to use for a dataset that is hierarchal? This site might help you put things into a conceptual framework and make a decision.</p>
<hr /><p>&nbsp;</p><p><iframe src="http://www.datavizcatalogue.com/" width="900" height="400">Your browser does not support iframes.</iframe></p>
<hr />
<h3>Three Compilations of Data Visualization Tools:</h3><p><a href="http://selection.datavisualization.ch/" target="_blank">Data Visualization</a><br />
A fairly extensive compilation of data visualization tools:</p>
<hr /><p><iframe src="http://selection.datavisualization.ch/" width="900" height="300">Your browser does not support iframes.</iframe></p>
<hr />
<h4></h4>
<h4><a href="http://www.visualisingdata.com/">Visualizing Data</a></h4><p>Another extensive compilation of data visualization tools. It is definitely worth a visit. Between this one and the one above, there isn&#8217;t much not covered.</p>
<h4><a href="http://10-open-source-projects-every-javascript-geo-dev-should-know-about/">10-open-source-projects-every-javascript-geo-dev-should-know-about</a></h4><p>This post on the ESRI blog is worth a look over, especially if you have map data locked into ESRI applications but want to do things in a more developer-centric and less GUI fashion.</p>
<h3>Galleries of Data Visualization Examples:</h3>
<h5 class="p1"><a href="http://Scientific/ Visualization Studio">Scientific Visualization Studio</a></h5>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">The Scientific Visualization Studio is out of NASA&#8217;s Goddard Space Flight Center. They make animated 2D and 3D visualizations. These look amazing on very large screens, especially if you have higher than normal resolution.  Download and run locally, rather than using the youtube player, to get the best picture possible. </span></p>
<h5 class="p1"><a href="https://github.com/mbostock/d3/wiki/Gallery" target="_blank">D3.js Visual Index</a></h5><p>There are a lot of data visualization libraries written in the JavaScript language. D3.js is the reigning champion. D3 (or Data Driven Documents) favors configuration over convention. The advantages are that it is very flexible and powerful. The disadvantage is it has more of a learning curve compared to other JavaScript data visualization libraries that favor convention.</p>
<h5><a href="http://bl.ocks.org/" target="_blank">Blocks</a> (D3.js)</h5>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Bl.ocks (pronounced “Blocks”) is a simple viewer for sharing code examples hosted on <a href="https://gist.github.com/"><span class="s2">GitHub Gist</span></a>. Anyone can use it to easily display their d3 visualizations. If you go to &#8220;popular&#8221; tab in the upper right corner of the Blocks website, you can see some of the most population visualization on Blocks.</span></p><p><a href="http://collection.marijerooze.nl/" target="_blank">collection.marijerooze.nl</a></p><p>A collection of over 465 data visualizations put together by Marije Rooze, an Amsterdam based front-end developer. Examples largely come from the NYTimes and Guardian newspapers. The ability to filter makes it a good way to find examples.</p>
<h5><a href="http://stamen.com/work/" target="_blank">Stamen</a></h5><p>A design studio focused on data visualization and mapping, Stamen produces some amazingly beautiful products for big clients like National Geographic. Definitely check them out if you have a map focus and want to be inspired/humbled.</p>
<h5><a href="http://roadtolarissa.com/" target="_blank">Road To Larissa</a></h5><p>A gallery of data visualizations made by Adam Pearce of Bloomberg Graphics.</p>
<h5><a href="http://www.smallmeans.com/new-york-times-infographics/" target="_blank">SmallMeans</a></h5><p>A gallery of favorited NYTimes graphics by a software engineering student.</p>
<h3>Data Visualization Blogs:</h3>
<h5><a href="http://flowingdata.com/" target="_blank">Flowing Data</a></h5><p>I suspect this is one of the most popular data visualization websites. It is the only one I have seen pop-up in my facebook feed several times</p>
<h5><a href="http://www.informationisbeautiful.net/" target="_blank">Information is Beautiful</a></h5><p>Run by David McCandless. This website has data visualization &#8220;best of&#8221; contests and lots of generally cool data visualizations.</p>
<h5><a href="http://feltron.com/">Nicholas Felton (website)</a></h5><p>More infographics than data visualizations, a big name worth checking out.</p><p><a href="http://feltron.tumblr.com/">Nicholar Felton (tumblr)</a></p><p>A curated selection put together by Felton. These are pieces of art as much as they are data visualizations.</p><p><a href="http://www.visualcinnamon.com/">Visual Cinnamon</a></p><p>Personal webpage of Nadieh Bremer who, in her own words, is a Astronomer-turned-Data-Scientist-turned-self-taught-Data-Visualization-Designer. In addition to her own work, which is stunning, she has a well curated list of internet resources and books on data visualization.</p><p><a href="http://fellinlovewithdata.com/" target="_blank">Fell In Love With Data</a></p><p>Not just pretty pictures, this blog has some excellent writing about what makes for good data visualizations. FILWD is edited by<a href="http://enrico.bertini.io/">Enrico Bertini</a>, Assistant Professor at the <a href="http://engineering.nyu.edu/">NYU Tandon School of Engineering</a>. He also has a podcast, <a href="http://datastori.es/">Data Stories</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/data-visualization-compilations/">Data Visualization Compilations</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/data-visualization-compilations/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">453</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tableau Data Visualization Animal Control Calls</title>
		<link>/tableau-data-visualization/</link>
		<comments>/tableau-data-visualization/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2016 20:39:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CartoDB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mapbox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Map]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Mapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opendata]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tableau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=364</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Tableau: Data Visualization Software (&#038; mapping)Tableau is similar to CartoDB and MapBox, which were discussed in earlier posts here and here. All are designed to allow the user to quickly drop in data and create visual representations of that data. All have free and paid versions. Tableau Public is the free version of Tableau. The main<a href="/tableau-data-visualization/">[...]</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/tableau-data-visualization/">Tableau Data Visualization Animal Control Calls</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Tableau: Data Visualization Software (& mapping)</h3><p>Tableau is similar to <a href="https://cartodb.com/" target="blank">CartoDB</a> and <a href="https://www.mapbox.com/" target="blank">MapBox</a>, which were discussed in earlier posts <a href="/cartodb-online-mapping/" target="blank">here</a> and <a href="/using-mapbox-an-online-map-service/" target="blank">here</a>. All are designed to allow the user to quickly drop in data and create visual representations of that data. All have free and paid versions. <a href="https://public.tableau.com/s/" target="blank">Tableau Public</a> is the free version of Tableau. The main limitations for Tableau Public vs. the paid version is more limited range of input data types (you still get xls and csv) and projects can only be saved to your public gallery.</p><p>What sets Tableau apart is <strong><em>Tableau</em><em><strong> is</strong>n&#8217;t just maps. It attempts to cover data visualization in general. </em></strong>Bar charts, pie charts, scatter plots, etc. Think of anything you have ever seen come out of Excel, plus some things you haven&#8217;t. Maps are just one more type of data visualization for Tableau. Tableau also excels at moving very quickly from &#8220;I have structured data&#8221; to &#8220;I have multiple visualizations of that data sliced multiple ways. It allows interactive visualization for the end-user too.&#8221;</p>
<div></div>
<div>
<div id="attachment_397" style="width: 330px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png" target="blank"><img data-attachment-id="397" data-permalink="/tableau-data-visualization/screen-shot-2016-01-12-at-2-56-18-pm/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png?fit=320%2C550" data-orig-size="320,550" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screen Shot 2016-01-12 at 2.56.18 PM" data-image-description="&lt;p&gt;Screenshot of menu options for different default data visualization types.&lt;/p&gt;
" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png?fit=175%2C300" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png?fit=320%2C550" class="size-full wp-image-397" src="https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png?resize=320%2C550" alt="Screenshot of menu options for different default data visualization types." width="320" height="550" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png?w=320 320w, https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png?resize=175%2C300 175w" sizes="(max-width: 320px) 100vw, 320px" data-recalc-dims="1" /></a></p>
<p class="wp-caption-text">Screenshot of menu options for different default data visualization types.</p>
</div>
<h3 style="text-align: left;">Houston Data Visualization Meet-up</h3>
<p style="text-align: left;">This post was prompted by two talks at a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Houston-Data-Visualization-Meetup/events/227238782/">recent</a><a href="http://www.meetup.com/Houston-Data-Visualization-Meetup/" target="blank">Houston Data Visualization</a> Meet-up. I attend meet-ups on data visualization, JavaScript, and python to see new things and get an idea what other people are working on locally. This meet-up was hosted at <a href="https://txrxlabs.org/" target="blank">TXRX labs</a>, which is a cool space if you ever have an opportunity to go. To quote their &#8220;about us&#8221; section:</p>
<blockquote><p><em>Established in 2008, TXRX Labs is a non-profit hackerspace for the greater Houston area. Housed in the East End District, we offer courses in and access to our rapid prototyping lab, woodshop, machineshop, electronics lab, and a wide variety of other tools. Our goal is to educate the public about technology and show how seemingly complex techniques can be used by anyone.</em></p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">The two mains talks at the Data Visualization Meet-up were on Tableau and used real estate data. I won&#8217;t attempt to replicate them here, but I will include a link to Clay Cohoon&#8217;s <a href="https://public.tableau.com/profile/clay.cahoon#!/" target="blank">public gallery</a> of visualizations. Clay delivered an entertaining talk that walked the audience through Tableau from data loading to sharing the final product. There is also a lot of great stuff on <a href="https://public.tableau.com/s/gallery">Tableau&#8217;s gallery</a>, basically a greatest hits collection.</p>
<h4 style="text-align: left;">A static image of Clay&#8217;s Visualization Being Built in Tableau Public:</h4><p><a href="https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png"><img data-attachment-id="410" data-permalink="/tableau-data-visualization/trustee/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png?fit=1360%2C768" data-orig-size="1360,768" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Trustee" data-image-description="&lt;p&gt;Image of Clay Cahoon&#8217;s visualization dashboard from his talk.&lt;/p&gt;
" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png?fit=300%2C169" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png?fit=640%2C361" class="size-full wp-image-410 aligncenter" src="https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png?resize=640%2C361" alt="Image of Clay Cahoon's visualization dashboard from his talk." width="640" height="361" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png?w=1360 1360w, https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png?resize=300%2C169 300w, https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png?resize=1024%2C578 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png?w=1280 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" data-recalc-dims="1" /></a></p>
</div>
<div>
<h4 style="text-align: left;"><em>A few take away&#8217;s from Clay Cohoon&#8217;s talk were:</em></h4>
<ol>
<li style="text-align: left;">There&#8217;s <strong>a lot of interactivity baked into Tableau</strong> that allows the end-user to click a data point or label and have other maps or graphs in the dashboard automatically update to show only data for that label or datapoint.</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">By right clicking on a point or axis, the <strong>end-user can bring up an option to download a selected portion of the data</strong> to their own computer.</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">By including an option for calculated fields, Tableau allows you to do some <strong>data crunching right in Tableau, </strong>in addition the main purpose of data visualization. This <strong>saves time</strong> as you don&#8217;t have to go all the way back to start just to normalize your data using Excel.</li>
</ol>
</div>
<h3>My Tableau Project: Animal Control Calls in 77009 Zip Code 2012-2015</h3><p>As I needed data to throw into Tableau, I decided to check out <a href="http://data.ohouston.org/ target=">Houston&#8217;s Open Data </a>portal. Mostly because I was curious what the data would look like, I decided to use <a href="http://data.ohouston.org/dataset/barc-animal-service-requests" target="blank">BARC call data</a> from the 77009 zip code. <a href="http://www.houstontx.gov/barc/aboutbarc.html" target="blank">BARC</a> is Houston&#8217;s city-run animal shelter. They respond to animal control calls from the public.</p><p>My main insights after being able to look at the data visually were: a sizable portion of the calls to BARC are cancelled instead of completed, wild-animal calls make up a very small percentage of total calls, and, although calls are pretty evenly distributed, the most expensive portion of the Houston Heights (SW portion of 77009 zip code) had less calls on average.</p>
<h4><em>A few take aways from creating this visualization were:</em></h4>
<ol>
<li>The time it takes to go from opening Tableau to having your first visualization is very short. In the meet-up talks, it was approximately 15 minutes. In my first time using the program, it took me maybe an hour.</li>
<li>The user interface is intuitive enough that I stopped watching a tutorial video after a couple of minutes. I made my way through pressing buttons and experimenting without any aggravating moments.</li>
<li>Something that Clay Cahoon brought up during his talk, and that I noticed as well, is that although Tableau is super fast and easy to create first draft visualizations, adjusting the &#8220;fine details&#8221; like fonts and line widths is not nearly as quick. This is not a huge program, perhaps only surprising, given everything else is so intuitive and fast.</li>
</ol><p>As you explore the visualization below, CLICK ON THE DATA. If you click on a map data point, it brings up extra data. If you click on the bar graph, it affects what is shown in the map. All this interactivity is baked into Tablea. Zero clicks were needed to make it happen.</p><p>You can bring up a new full-window view by <strong>clicking <a href="https://public.tableau.com/profile/justin.gosses#!/vizhome/Houston77009Zipcode-CallstoAnimalControl/Dashboard_Small" target="blank">here</a></strong>.</p><p>&nbsp;</p><p><embed src="https://public.tableau.com/shared/6K6WP2SGJ?:display_count=yes" width="1500" height="900"></embed></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/tableau-data-visualization/">Tableau Data Visualization Animal Control Calls</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/tableau-data-visualization/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">364</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>ArcGIS Online WebMaps and MapApps</title>
		<link>/arcgis_webmaps/</link>
		<comments>/arcgis_webmaps/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 20:25:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ArcGIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CartoDB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[galveston]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[KayakMap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mapbox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Map]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[python and GIS]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=233</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>ArcGIS:For those that might be new to GIS, ArcGIS is the default enterprise GIS solution. This isn&#8217;t a great comparison, but it is similar to Microsoft in the 1990s but less evil and with no Apple. The company behind ArcGIS is ESRI. They provide a variety of geospatial products and services; ArcGIS Desktop, ArcGIS Server,<a href="/arcgis_webmaps/">[...]</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/arcgis_webmaps/">ArcGIS Online WebMaps and MapApps</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>ArcGIS:</h4><p>For those that might be new to GIS, ArcGIS is the default enterprise GIS solution. This isn&#8217;t a great comparison, but it is similar to Microsoft in the 1990s but less evil and with no Apple. The company behind ArcGIS is ESRI. They provide a variety of geospatial products and services; ArcGIS Desktop, ArcGIS Server, ArcGIS Online, etc. All of them do geospatial analysis, just differently. ArcGIS desktop is going to be what someone with &#8220;Geospatial Analyst&#8221; in their job title will be using on most days in a business setting. ArcGIS Server, as the name implies, is about supplying data to large organizations via a server. ArcGIS Online is geared to sharing maps through web maps and web apps.</p>
<h4>Web Map vs. Map App</h4><p>Before we go any further, let&#8217;s get some terminology out of the way. Using ArcGIS Online, you can build either a web map or a map app. A Web map, for our purposes, is going to be something you&#8217;re probably going to embed into your own website. It might have a zoom feature and a legend, but it won&#8217;t have too many bells and whistles. A map app by contrast is more like a stand alone web application that exists as a single page with its own url address. Think of it as its own website. ArcGIS Online has both a gallery of Map App themes to choose from and a Map App builder. If you&#8217;re familiar WordPress. It is almost like WordPress for maps. There are widgets for adding a measuring button, a search tab to find locations, image analysis, feature editing, and various other options.</p>
<h4>Comparison to Cartodb, Mapbox, etc.</h4><p>ArcGIS Online and the other online map services all try to be the service you use to easily embed maps in your webpage or share urls to your map on their site. ArcGIS online products have the advantage of the ESRI name, established support, and being one part of a wider enterprise solution.</p><p>For the purpose of this blog post (and as refresher before going to a GIS web development hackathon) I built a map using ArcGIS online, which is below. It was built with a small subset of the data I&#8217;m using for a map on Houston recreational paddling experiences. I also turned that map into a Map App.</p><p><b>The map app can be found at this <a href="https://gosses.maps.arcgis.com/apps/webappviewer/index.html?id=b432c7a82e8f4e42958df3f955f781e1" target="blank">link</a></b>, which will open another tab on your browser with a full page map app. In addition to opening up full screen,<span style="text-decoration: underline;"> the map app makes it possible to turn layers on and off, measure distance, get directions from your location to boat launches on the map, and brings the legend up as an option</span>.</p><p>My general impression was if all I needed was a really quick and simple map that only included a basemap and a few points, I&#8217;d probably go with Mapbox. The upload and selection of data is a little slower with ArcGIS Online. Plus, there are more buttons to push between start and finish. For very complicated maps, I suspect ArcGIS online would likely be what I&#8217;d use, because I could more easily build the map in desktop mode, where I&#8217;m not slowed by internet service and browser constraints, and then transition it online.</p><p><del>One disappointment I did have with ArcGIS online was the limited data types you were allowed to upload to your online map. In addition to limited data types, shape files couldn&#8217;t be above a certain size or number of features. I ended up having to dissolve every shapefile I uploaded, resulting in lost of attribute information I would have liked to be included in the map. Specifically, the names of small stream segments and stream environmental health information. As this was a quick trial map, I didn&#8217;t worry too much about it, but in the future I&#8217;ll likely have to use python to split shapefiles into many shapfiles by attribute criteria and then load up a larger total number of shapefiles. Doing it by hand would be too slower and annoying.</del>  <em> <strong>EDITED: </strong>It turns out I could upload it directly. I just needed to do it as a feature service instead of shape files. Thanks to Nick for the correction. </em></p><p>The best thing ArcGIS Online has going for it for putting very easy to moderate complexity maps on the web is the pre-built MapApp themes. Their <a href="http://doc.arcgis.com/en/web-appbuilder/" target="blank">WebApp gallery</a> has a portfolio of some of standard themes and others that people have built. If you&#8217;re a full blown web developer you might choose to use leaflet.js and more general javascript to build these types of polished feature rich map applications. If you don&#8217;t know what javascript is, ArcGIS Online Web App builder might be your best option.</p><p><em><strong>EDIT:</strong> For more information on ArcGIS online development tools, check out this <a href="/arcgis_hackathon/" target="blank"> more recent post</a>.</em></p><p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="embed-container"><iframe title="Kayak_Map_Rough1" src="https://gosses.maps.arcgis.com/apps/Embed/index.html?webmap=3c30321ce3a943409b37a966aa6c0360&extent=-96.031,29.1817,-94.0026,30.1186&home=true&zoom=true&scale=true&search=true&searchextent=true&legend=true&basemap_toggle=true&alt_basemap=hybrid&disable_scroll=true&theme=light" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div><p>Click the double arrow in the upper left corner &lt;&lt; to see the map legend. If you click the image in the lower left corner, the basemap will change to satellite imagery. Impaired segments are those with environmental issues according to the TCEQ or Texas Commission on Environmental Quality.</p><p><a href="http://arcg.is/1NRH4gK" target="blank">link to the map above that opens in a new tab</a></p><p><a href="https://gosses.maps.arcgis.com/apps/webappviewer/index.html?id=b432c7a82e8f4e42958df3f955f781e1" target="blank">link to <span style="color: #ff0000;"><strong>full screen map app</strong> </span>with additional features like legend, turning layers on and off, multiple basemap options, attribute table views, lat/long at mouse position, and directions.</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/arcgis_webmaps/">ArcGIS Online WebMaps and MapApps</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/arcgis_webmaps/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
	<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">233</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
