<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" >

<channel>
	<title>HTML &#8211; Justin Gosses Home</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/html/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Geology, GIS, and CODE + Resumes</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2019 00:35:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9.11</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://i1.wp.com/justingosses.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/cropped-JustinGosses_logo.jpg?fit=32%2C32</url>
	<title>HTML &#8211; Justin Gosses Home</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">102288347</site>	<item>
		<title>What do I get out of conferences?</title>
		<link>/what-do-i-get-out-of-conferences/</link>
		<comments>/what-do-i-get-out-of-conferences/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2017 06:23:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AAPG]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Agile Geoscience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conference]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[convention]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hackathon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HTML]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NASA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Map]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[python]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[talks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tutorials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=894</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Four conferences, two hackathons, and a lot of meet-ups: Analyzing what I&#8217;ve gotten from technical gatherings outside of work this year&#160; Part 1 &#8211;  The PremiseOver the last year, I&#8217;ve been lucky to attend more than my usual number of conferences, meetups, and hackathons. Some of the events were paid by work, some were paid<a href="/what-do-i-get-out-of-conferences/">[...]</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/what-do-i-get-out-of-conferences/">What do I get out of conferences?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 style="text-align: center;">Four conferences, two hackathons, and a lot of meet-ups: Analyzing what I&#8217;ve gotten from technical gatherings outside of work this year</h3><p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Part 1 &#8211;  The Premise</h2><p>Over the last year, I&#8217;ve been lucky to attend more than my usual number of conferences, meetups, and hackathons. Some of the events were paid by work, some were paid by me, and some were free. As my last event for 2017 is coming up, I&#8217;m asking myself two questions.</p><p><strong>First, what did I get out of the gatherings I attended?</strong></p><p><strong>Second, what types of events should I attend next year in order to maximize the benefits I&#8217;m interested in?</strong></p><p>As I see it, attending technical gatherings can have a range of benefits:</p>
<ol>
<li>People
<ul>
<li>Meet leaders in the field</li>
<li>Make new contacts and catch up with old contacts</li>
<li>Meet many vendors at once</li>
<li>Market yourself and your company</li>
<li>Gain a better understanding of where your skills and knowledge rank</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Skills
<ul>
<li>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</li>
<li>Learn what to do or not do from others&#8217; experiences</li>
<li>Attend a tutorial and take the first few steps in a new skill with someone there to lead you</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Knowledge of the environment beyond your immediate organization
<ul>
<li>Gain exposure to a wide range of tools, methods, and applications</li>
<li>Learn what is upcoming and new</li>
<li>Understand how the larger market or community is evolving</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol><p>Working under the assumption that understanding what I got out of the past events will help me plan ahead, I&#8217;ve compiled a description of various technical gatherings I&#8217;ve attended over the last twelve months.</p>
<h2>Part 2 &#8211; The Data</h2><p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;">AAPG ACE 2017</h2>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">What is it?</span></h5><p><a href="http://www.aapg.org/">American Association of Petroleum Geologist</a>s Annual <a href="http://ace.aapg.org/2017/about">Conference & Exhibit</a>. It is the main conference for petroleum geologists and the largest of several AAPG conferences. The conference can cost between $65 and $650 depending on whether you are a student and when you purchase.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>Geologists in the oil and gas industry and some geophysicists. Engineers have their own conferences. The focus is on technical aspects as opposed to business environment or deal making.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>Most people dress like they do at work, which is to say dress pants, dress pants, and collared shirts if you&#8217;re a guy or the equivalent if female. If you&#8217;re presenting or looking for work, you might wear a suit and tie. A few people wear jeans. There are no funny t-shirts.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p>This year it was in Houston. The conference moves every year between North American oil industry centers like Houston, Long Beach, Calgary, and Denver.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p>The average over the last 5 years has been <a href="http://www.aapg.org/events/conferences/ace">6,900</a>.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>Most of the talks follow the pattern of a typical science talk explaining what they did in very rough terms and what their conclusions are.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Make new contacts and catch up with old contacts</em>
<ul>
<li>AAPG ACE was very good for making connections with people I haven&#8217;t seen in a while now that I&#8217;m out of the oil and gas industry.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Learn what is upcoming and new</em>
<ul>
<li>It is also a great place for seeing what is at the forefront of the intersection between industry and academia in geology as various research consortia present talks and posters.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Benefit areas that were lacking</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</em></li>
<li><em>Attend a tutorial and take the first few steps in a new skill with someone to lead you</em>
<ul>
<li>Compared with tech conferences, the range of talk types is limited. There are almost no &#8220;how to&#8221; or &#8220;when to use blank method&#8221; talks. Everything is in the science talk mold.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>AAPG was great for catching up with people and getting a peek at what other people are working on, even if it is a small peak. Some of the talks can be frustratingly vague due to intellectual property constraints. Field trips provide some opportunity for improving technical skills, but they typically cost enough that you&#8217;ll only attend if your employer is paying. The main convention talks tend to focus on what someone has been done rather than what you could do.</p><p>If you&#8217;re interested in hearing more about what geology conferences are missing and what they might be able to learn from certain tech conference models, the Undersampled Radio podcast recent had a great conversation on this topic starting at 30 minutes into <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vCeNA9btD9E"> episode 46</a>.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;">SXSW Interactive</h2>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;"> What is it?</span></h5><p>South by Southwest is a mega-conference in which the &#8220;<a href="https://www.sxsw.com/festivals/interactive/">Interactive</a>&#8221; sub-conference focuses on digital, internet, intelligent future, social impact, journalism, start-ups, AR/VR, music industry, sports industry, and the workplace. The interactive sub-conference takes place over 5 days and overlaps with the education, music, film, and comedy sub-conferences. More information <a href="https://www.sxsw.com/festivals/interactive/">here</a>. SXSW Interactive tickets cost $1,225.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>Marketing companies, hip people, students who volunteer to get their otherwise expensive tickets paid for, and people in the digital space who want to see what is new or make connections.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>Varies from nerdy t-shirts to professor jackets with elbow patches. If business casual, a little on the fashionable side.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p>Austin, every year.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_by_Southwest">30,621</a></p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>The talks here range from &#8220;this is new&#8221; to &#8220;we did and you can too&#8221; to &#8220;let&#8217;s talk about the context of something&#8221; to &#8220;fluff and buzzwords&#8221;.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Meet leaders in the field</em>
<ul>
<li>I talked with <a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~jheer/">Vint Cerf</a>, one of the &#8220;fathers of the internet, and <a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~jheer/">Jeffrey Heer </a>, a professor who has had a role in many key data visualization code libraries, such as <a href="https://vega.github.io/vega/">vega.js</a>, <a href="https://vincent.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">vincent.py</a>, and <a href="https://d3js.org/">d3.js</a>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Understand trends in the larger market or community. Learn what is new</em></li>
<li><em>Learn what is upcoming and new</em>
<ul>
<li>Saw a lot in regards to VR/AR that was cutting edge.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Understand how the larger market or community is evolving</em></li>
<li><em>Meet many vendors at once</em>
<ul>
<li>Largest exhibit showroom of any conference in this list.</li>
<li>Met with two vendors afterward and used the experience to benchmark against other vendors post conference</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet people doing similar work and learn from their experiences</em>
<ul>
<li>There were several talks that inspired ideas for future projects based on what similar teams had done in other organizations. Post-talk discussions were great for identifying failures to avoid in upcoming projects.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Benefit areas that were lacking</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</em>
<ul>
<li>Talks tend to lack technical depth.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Attend a tutorial and take the first few steps in a new skill with someone to lead you</em>
<ul>
<li>There weren&#8217;t any tutorials.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li>There are more talks about products and solutions than methods or tools.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>There were some great talks that inspired potential future projects, but meeting people was the more valuable activity at SXSW. Perhaps for that reason, there were <a href="http://schedule.sxsw.com/2017/03/10/events/conference/Interactive/type/panel">several time slots</a> for people to just &#8220;meet-up&#8221; in a room and talk about a specific topic.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">PyCon2017</h3>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">What is it?</span></h5><p><a href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/">PyCon</a> is the largest conference for Python developers. Web development and data analytics are the two focus areas. The base convention ticket for PyCon is $600 for corporate, $350 for individuals, and $125 for students. If sign-up for the max amount of tutorials, total ticket price can be up to $1200.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>People who write code in Python. The male/female ratio at PyCon was maybe 70/30, which made it the most unbalanced of all the conferences.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>There&#8217;s a range, but, compared to the other conferences, it was high on nerdy t-shirts and low on formal or business clothes.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p>PyCon was held in Portland, Oregon. PyCon holds their conferences in the same city for two years before switching, which minimizes costs and planning requirements. Next year, it will be in Cleveland, Ohio. Previous to Portland, it was in Montreal.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Python_Conference">3,391</a> badges were picked up from registration.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>PyCon is split into two days of tutorials, three days of talks, and then four days of open-source development sprints.</p>
<ul>
<li>Tutorials are half a day in length. Topics included Bayesian machine learning, time series analysis, network analysis, using flask for microservices, <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/schedule/tutorials/">etc</a>.</li>
<li>During the main convention, talks ranged in style from:
<ul>
<li>We did this with Python</li>
<li>Best practice in some aspect of writing code</li>
<li>The &#8220;craft&#8221; of some part of writing python code</li>
<li>Introduction to a new python module or open-source project</li>
<li>Introduction to some activity that can be done with python</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>During the sprints, open-source Python <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/community/sprints/">projects</a> are built or extended.</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Meet leaders in the field</em>
<ul>
<li>Ended up at a bar with <a href="https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/the-birth-and-death-of-javascript">Gary Bernhardt</a> , who runs &#8220;destroyallsoftware.com&#8221;, and <a href="https://www.kennethreitz.org/projects/">Kenneth Reitz</a>, the main author of the &#8220;requests&#8221; python module.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Attend a tutorial and take the first few steps in a new skill with someone to lead you</em>
<ul>
<li>Attended excellent half-day <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/schedule/tutorials/">tutorials</a> on Bayesian machine learning, time series analysis, and MQTT protocol.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</em>
<ul>
<li>Several talks were on the &#8220;craft&#8221; of some aspect of writing code, examples included documentation, testing, and sever reliability.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet people doing similar work and learn from their experiences</em>
<ul>
<li>Talked to a variety of people doing similar work in different organizations and learned how their teams and approaches differ from mine.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li>Got exposure to a range of new modules and methods and what they could be used for.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Benefit areas that were lacking</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Meet many vendors at once</em>
<ul>
<li>Although there was an exhibit floor, the number and diversity of vendors were a bit lacking for a conference of that size.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>PyCon was excellent for picking up bits of new skills and improving my understanding of what python modules I might be able to use in future projects. Many of the talks had a focus on leaving the audience with something useful, which made it a great conference for learning. My <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zm0x1uLg-SKGI4nbu-_ND_44Bycl_wo4tTxVpjDDC6g/edit?usp=sharing">notes</a> have links to the slides and Jupyter Notebooks used by some of the presenters.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">Johnson Space Center Data Science Day</h3>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">What is it?</span></h5><p><a href="https://fal.jsc.nasa.gov/DSD/">Data Science Day 2.0</a> was two days of talks around various aspects of data science, data visualization, and analytics. It was free to attend.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>A mixture of NASA civil servants, NASA contractors, vendors, and the public who were interested in the subject matter.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>Mostly business casual with some suits and ties.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p>Gilruth Center just outside Johnson Space Center, Houston, Texas.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p>I estimate 200-350.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>Talks ranged from programming newbie talks to &#8220;we built this&#8221; talks to &#8220;this capability exists&#8221; talks.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li>Got exposure to skills and methods I haven&#8217;t used myself yet.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet people doing similar work and learn from their experiences</em>
<ul>
<li>Made connections to others at Johnson Space Center who were interested in working with our team.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Market yourself and your company</em>
<ul>
<li>Presented a <a href="http://slides.com/justingosses/history_data_visualization_tools#/">talk</a> on the history of digital data visualization tools.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Benefit areas that were lacking</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</em>
<ul>
<li>There weren&#8217;t many talks about the craft of data science or data visualization.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>Given Johnson Space Center is a rather spread out campus with many buildings, events like this are really valuable for communicating about skills that cross normal organizational boundaries. Attending an event of this type wouldn&#8217;t replace something like PyCon, however, due to the lack of tutorials and in-depth skill sessions.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">Various Houston Tech Meetups</h3>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">What is it?</span></h5><p>There are a variety of <a href="https://www.meetup.com/find/?allMeetups=false&keywords=tech&radius=25&userFreeform=Houston%2C+TX&mcId=c77001&mcName=Houston%2C+TX&sort=default">meetups</a> in Houston that focus on t<a href="https://www.meetup.com/Collabonauts/">ech</a>, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/houston-js/events/240279389/">web development</a>, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Houston-VR-Developers/events/239502556/">virtual reality</a>, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Hackster-Hardware-Meetup-Houston/events/240263187/">IoT</a>, and <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Houston-Energy-Data-Science-Meetup/">data science</a>. These are typically 1.5 to 4-hour meetings around various topics held every month or two somewhere in Houston. I regularly go to ones on <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Houston-Data-Visualization-Meetup/">data visualization</a>, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/houston-js/">JavaScript</a>, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/python-web-houston/">Python</a>, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sketchcity/events/239311484/">civic projects</a>, and <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Houston-React-Js-Group/events/240297939/">front-end web development</a>. They are free to attend although sometimes donations are requested for snacks.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>Anyone interested in the subject. Attendees range from complete newbies to professional developers.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>Casual to whatever people were wearing at work.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p>It varies from civic community spaces to tech companies to coffee shops and bars.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p>5-75, but many times a year.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>The two most common types are &#8220;introduction to blank&#8221; talks and &#8220;this is what I have done with blank&#8221; talks. My favorite is Houston data visualization meetup&#8217;s monthly &#8220;data jams&#8221;. A cleaned dataset is provided. Participants have 4 hours to build data visualizations with any code library or software tool they care to apply. This is a great way to learn about new tools and methods for data visualization.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li>You&#8217;ll get exposure to a wide range of tools and approaches for a single topic.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet people doing similar work and learn from their experiences</em>
<ul>
<li>Make connections across industries and organizations in Houston.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Make new contacts and catch up with old contacts</li>
<li><em>Market yourself and your company</em>
<ul>
<li>The easiest place to present a talk or contribute to the local developer community.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Benefit areas that were lacking</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Meet many vendors at once</em>
<ul>
<li>Vendor pitches are generally frowned upon, so there aren&#8217;t that many. Energy industry meetups are the exception.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet leaders in the field</em>
<ul>
<li>Unfortunately, Houston is not much of a tech hub, so there aren&#8217;t that many big names here.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>The main benefit of meetups for me is the exposure to a wide range of tools applied to the same topic or problem. This saves me a great amount of time in terms of researching and comparing new tools myself.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">Space-Apps Challenge Houston</h3>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">What is it?</span></h5><p>A <a href="https://2017.spaceappschallenge.org/">global hackathon</a> that uses NASA data, but is hosted locally in many cities around the world. This was the first year the event was hosted in Houston for several years. Participants form teams and have two days to hack together a solution, usually a web application but sometimes hardware, to one of the NASA <a href="https://2017.spaceappschallenge.org/challenges/">challenges</a>. It is free to attend. There was sponsor swag, coffee, beer, and food from <a href="http://stationhouston.com/">Station Houston</a>, Amazon Web Services, Intel, and <a href="https://www.yelp.com/biz/morningstar-houston">Morningstar Coffee</a>. I was a technical mentor during the event, not a participant.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>Participants at the Houston event included high school students with a little coding knowledge, recent coding boot camp graduates, computer science undergraduates, IBM engineers, and professional web developers.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>85% jeans & t-shirt and 15% slightly fancier.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p><a href="https://www.theironyard.com/locations/houston">The Iron Yard</a>, a coding boot camp with locations in various cities, including Houston.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p>~30</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>Aside from a 20-minute talk on NASA civilian science, the time was spent working on each team&#8217;s project. You can read more about some of the projects created at the Houston event <a href="https://2017.spaceappschallenge.org/locations/houston/">here</a>.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li>Two of the teams used technologies I hadn&#8217;t worked with before.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</em></li>
<li><em>Make new contacts and catch up with old contacts</em>
<ul>
<li>Made connections with several or the participants</li>
<li>Worked with <a href="http://stationhouston.com/">Station</a>, <a href="https://www.theironyard.com/locations/houston">The Iron Yard</a>, and several <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Houston-Data-Visualization-Meetup/">meet-up group</a> leads to organize the event.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Benefit areas that were lacking</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Meet leaders in the field</em></li>
<li><em>Meet people doing similar work and learn from their experiences</em></li>
<li><em>Meet many vendors at once</em></li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>As a participant, hackathons are great for taking a method or technology that is new to you, cramming as much about it into your brain as possible, and then applying it in a very intense, short period of time. As a technical mentor, who also did a bit of event organization, it is a great way to expand your network, learn from others, and you get some of the previously mentioned technical benefits too.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">Agile Scientific Paris Subsurface Hackathon</h3>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">What is it?</span></h5><p>A hackathon associated with a geological society conference in Paris.  This is one of <a href="https://agilescientific.com/">Agile Scientific&#8217;s</a> hackathons that take place 1-3 times a year at geology and geophysics conferences. Total is co-organizing it. It is free to attend.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Who goes?</span></h5><p>Geologists and geophysicists who know how to code, usually in Python. Web development skills are typically sparse. Several people, including myself, will be participating as &#8220;robots&#8221;. This means I&#8217;ll be teleconferencing into the hackathon and my face will be appearing on a little laptop there.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Dress?</span></h5><p>Most of the on-location participants will be French, so I&#8217;m assuming they will likely be better dressed than me.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Where?</span></h5><p>Virtual & Paris.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">How big?</span></h5><p>Not sure as it hasn&#8217;t happened yet, but looks to be around 50.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Types of talks?</span></h5><p>There will likely be an introduction talk and then lots of coding.</p>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Main Benefits for me</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li>This always seems to happen at hackathons.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;
<ul>
<li>A lot of my coding ability was picked up after I left oil and gas, so it will be nice to work with geological datasets.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Make new contacts and catch up with old contacts
<ul>
<li>Several of the participants are people I know from a previous hackathon.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h5><span style="color: #008000;">Summary</span></h5><p>I&#8217;m hoping to use this as an opportunity to apply a new skill area that I&#8217;ll be using at work eventually but haven&#8217;t had much opportunity to use yet. Possibilities include time-series analysis, deep-learning, web-scraping, and natural language processing.</p>
<h2>Part 3  &#8211;  The Analysis</h2>
<h3>Ranking of which events had which benefits the most</h3><p>Based on the notes above, I&#8217;ve ranked the events in terms of how well they fulfilled each benefit in my list. The event that most fulfilled each benefit is in <span style="color: #ff0000;">red<span style="color: #000000;">, with second in</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">purple</span><span style="color: #000000;">, etc</span></span>.</p>
<ol>
<li>People
<ul>
<li><em>Meet leaders in the field</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">SXSW &</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">PyCon</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet people doing similar work and learn from their experiences</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff6600;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Meet-ups</span>,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">PyCon</span><span style="color: #ff9900;"><span style="color: #cc99ff;">,</span> <span style="color: #99cc00;">JSC Data Science Day<span style="color: #99ccff;">,</span></span><span style="color: #99ccff;"> and meetups</span></span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Make new contacts and catch up with old contacts</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">AAPG,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">meetups,</span> <span style="color: #99cc00;">and PyCon</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Meet many vendors at once</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">SXSW <span style="color: #cc99ff;">and</span></span><span style="color: #cc99ff;"> AAPG</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Market yourself and your company</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #ff0000;">SXSW,</span><span style="color: #cc99ff;"> PyCON,</span><span style="color: #993300;"> </span><span style="color: #ff9900;"><span style="color: #99cc00;">AAPG,</span> <span style="color: #99ccff;">and meetups</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Gain a better understanding of where your skills and knowledge rank</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">PyCon,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">hackathons, </span><span style="color: #99cc00;">and meetups</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Skills
<ul>
<li><em>Pick up new &#8220;tricks of the trade&#8221;</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff6600;"><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Hackathons,</span><span style="color: #cc99ff;"> PyCon,</span></span></span> <span style="color: #99cc00;">meet-ups</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Learn what to do or not do from others&#8217; experiences</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">PyCon,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">meet-ups, </span><span style="color: #99cc00;">JSC Data Science Day</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Attend a tutorial and take the first few steps in a new skill with someone to lead you</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">PyCon,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">meet-ups, </span><span style="color: #99cc00;">hackathon</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Knowledge of the environment beyond your immediate organization
<ul>
<li><em>Learn about the larger range of tools, methods, and applications out there</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">PyCon,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">meet-ups, </span><span style="color: #99cc00;">JSC Data Science Day,</span><span style="color: #99ccff;"> SXSW</span><br />
</span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Understand trends in the larger market or community</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">SXSW,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">meet-ups,</span> <span style="color: #99cc00;">PyCon</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Learn what is new</em>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #993300;"><span style="color: #ff0000;"><span style="color: #ff6600;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">PyCon,</span> <span style="color: #cc99ff;">SXSW,</span></span></span> <span style="color: #99cc00;">JSC Data Science Day</span></span></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h3>Discussion</h3><p>Some types of events I might not want to go to every year. Other types of events I would go every year, but I might trade one conference for another with a similar style but different focus area.</p>
<h5>SXSW Interactive or another large conference of this type</h5><p>SXSW Interactive is great for getting a wide view of what is new and upcoming, but I&#8217;m not sure I need to go to it, or a conference like it, more than once every two to three years, even on a team that is responsible for keeping up with what is new.</p>
<h5>AAPG or another large science or professional association conference</h5><p>AAPG is great in terms of what it tries to be, a science conference for oil and gas geologists, but there are definitely <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vCeNA9btD9E">some aspects</a> of tech and computer language specific conferences that science and industry conferences could learn from. In-depth half-day tutorials, how-to sessions, and skill-building activities are all things that could be done in that conference space but just aren&#8217;t. A similar conference to this one, but in a computer science domain, would be <a href="https://www.ieee.org/conferences_events/index.html">IEEE</a>.</p>
<h5>PyCon or similar tech conference</h5><p>PyCon had a wide range of benefits, including tutorials and &#8220;how to do this activity well&#8221; talks that are not always present at other technical gatherings. The year before I went to <a href="https://pydata.org/chicago2016/">PyData in Chicago</a>, which, although a smaller conference, had a similar range of talks. A conference that might be similar but with a different focus is <a href="https://scipy2017.scipy.org/ehome/index.php?eventid=220975&">SciPy</a>.</p>
<h5>Hackathons</h5><p>They are great at both putting you in contact with the local developer community and showing you the range of approaching to a topic. However, they are intense. I participate or help out with 1-2 a year. More than that might be too much. I&#8217;ll do Space-Apps Houston again as there is definitely some value there both to me and to the community. Also, it is Houston! It was embarrassing there were several years when over a hundred Space-Apps hackathon events occurred globally, but there wasn&#8217;t an event in Houston. An alternative option that I seem to always be out of town for is the <a href="http://houstonhackathon.com/">Houston Hackathon</a>.</p>
<h5>Johnson Space Center Data Science Day or similar 1-2 day, &lt;300 people,  local event.</h5><p>Johnson Space Center Data Science Day is useful for making local and NASA specific people connections and seeing what others are working on, however, it can&#8217;t replace something like PyCon or PyData for learning new skills. I&#8217;ll attend and present, but I don&#8217;t really count it as a learning opportunity in the same way. Similar type one to two-day speaker events are held at Rice University focusing on big data and <a href="http://ml2017.rice.edu/">machine learning</a>.</p>
<h5>Houston tech meetups</h5><p>Tech meet-ups are my bread and butter learning opportunity. The combination of free, relatively easy to fit in your schedule as you don&#8217;t have to take days off, and leading directly into side projects works out well for me, especially as someone relatively new to writing code for a living. How many meetups I attend will depend on my schedule and number of side projects, which is difficult to predict in advance.</p>
<h3>Next year plans</h3>
<h5><em>Attend 0-1</em></h5><p>AAPG and SXSW style conferences have value but a more narrow range of benefits that ranks secondary to me right now. If options for travel and training are limited, I would focus my budget elsewhere next year.</p>
<h5><em>Attend many, present at 1+, and organize at least 1</em></h5><p>Tech meetups and hackathons are great in that they&#8217;re free, local, and there&#8217;s something you could attend multiple times a week if you wanted, at least in a major US city. That frequency also represents a burn-out danger, however, so I&#8217;ll probably attend the same amount or shift to attending a little less next year.</p>
<h5><em>Attend 1+ and present at 1+</em></h5><p>JSC Data Science Day is a great way to make local connections in a large and spread out organization, but I wouldn&#8217;t consider it a replacement for training or a major conference.</p>
<h5><em>Attend 1 (consider presenting)</em></h5><p>PyCon and similar-type conferences probably offer the most value of the options examined due to the presence of many tutorials and &#8220;craft of coding&#8221; talks. My top focus for planning which conference to attend next year will be on finding a good PyCon-style conference that covers slightly different terrain but is still very applicable to work.</p>
<h3>Conclusion</h3><p>Different outside of work technical gatherings have different benefits. An exercise like this helps organize experiences into data that is easier to analyze. My conclusions on what types of conferences are the most useful for me this year and next reflects what benefits I value the most right now. My main focus is on building skills and learning new tools, which shows up in my future conference preferences.</p><p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/what-do-i-get-out-of-conferences/">What do I get out of conferences?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/what-do-i-get-out-of-conferences/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">894</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Data Visualization Compilations</title>
		<link>/data-visualization-compilations/</link>
		<comments>/data-visualization-compilations/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2016 04:40:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CartoDB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CSS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Front-End]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HTML]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[javascript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mapbox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Map]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Mapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=453</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>A Compilation of Data Visualization Compilations:There are a wide variety of tools out there for data visualization. Some nice people have come up with compilations of their favorite tools. Other people have created galleries of really outstanding data visualizations that you can use as inspiration. Over the past year, I&#8217;ve bookmarked a lot of them.<a href="/data-visualization-compilations/">[...]</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/data-visualization-compilations/">Data Visualization Compilations</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>A Compilation of Data Visualization Compilations:</h3><p>There are a wide variety of tools out there for data visualization. Some nice people have come up with compilations of their favorite tools. Other people have created galleries of really outstanding data visualizations that you can use as inspiration. Over the past year, I&#8217;ve bookmarked a lot of them. This post is a curated compilation of compilations. If you&#8217;re interested in learning about data visualization on the web, this post might save you some time digging around the internet. Alternatively, it might be a massive time sink.</p>
<h3>Catalog of Data Visualization Types:</h3>
<h4><a href="http://www.datavizcatalogue.com/" target="_blank">Dataviz Catalogue</a></h4><p>This is a great site for thinking about, or discussing with others, the various advantages and disadvantages of different data visualization styles. Not sure what data visualization style to use for a dataset that is hierarchal? This site might help you put things into a conceptual framework and make a decision.</p>
<hr /><p>&nbsp;</p><p><iframe src="http://www.datavizcatalogue.com/" width="900" height="400">Your browser does not support iframes.</iframe></p>
<hr />
<h3>Three Compilations of Data Visualization Tools:</h3><p><a href="http://selection.datavisualization.ch/" target="_blank">Data Visualization</a><br />
A fairly extensive compilation of data visualization tools:</p>
<hr /><p><iframe src="http://selection.datavisualization.ch/" width="900" height="300">Your browser does not support iframes.</iframe></p>
<hr />
<h4></h4>
<h4><a href="http://www.visualisingdata.com/">Visualizing Data</a></h4><p>Another extensive compilation of data visualization tools. It is definitely worth a visit. Between this one and the one above, there isn&#8217;t much not covered.</p>
<h4><a href="http://10-open-source-projects-every-javascript-geo-dev-should-know-about/">10-open-source-projects-every-javascript-geo-dev-should-know-about</a></h4><p>This post on the ESRI blog is worth a look over, especially if you have map data locked into ESRI applications but want to do things in a more developer-centric and less GUI fashion.</p>
<h3>Galleries of Data Visualization Examples:</h3>
<h5 class="p1"><a href="http://Scientific/ Visualization Studio">Scientific Visualization Studio</a></h5>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">The Scientific Visualization Studio is out of NASA&#8217;s Goddard Space Flight Center. They make animated 2D and 3D visualizations. These look amazing on very large screens, especially if you have higher than normal resolution.  Download and run locally, rather than using the youtube player, to get the best picture possible. </span></p>
<h5 class="p1"><a href="https://github.com/mbostock/d3/wiki/Gallery" target="_blank">D3.js Visual Index</a></h5><p>There are a lot of data visualization libraries written in the JavaScript language. D3.js is the reigning champion. D3 (or Data Driven Documents) favors configuration over convention. The advantages are that it is very flexible and powerful. The disadvantage is it has more of a learning curve compared to other JavaScript data visualization libraries that favor convention.</p>
<h5><a href="http://bl.ocks.org/" target="_blank">Blocks</a> (D3.js)</h5>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Bl.ocks (pronounced “Blocks”) is a simple viewer for sharing code examples hosted on <a href="https://gist.github.com/"><span class="s2">GitHub Gist</span></a>. Anyone can use it to easily display their d3 visualizations. If you go to &#8220;popular&#8221; tab in the upper right corner of the Blocks website, you can see some of the most population visualization on Blocks.</span></p><p><a href="http://collection.marijerooze.nl/" target="_blank">collection.marijerooze.nl</a></p><p>A collection of over 465 data visualizations put together by Marije Rooze, an Amsterdam based front-end developer. Examples largely come from the NYTimes and Guardian newspapers. The ability to filter makes it a good way to find examples.</p>
<h5><a href="http://stamen.com/work/" target="_blank">Stamen</a></h5><p>A design studio focused on data visualization and mapping, Stamen produces some amazingly beautiful products for big clients like National Geographic. Definitely check them out if you have a map focus and want to be inspired/humbled.</p>
<h5><a href="http://roadtolarissa.com/" target="_blank">Road To Larissa</a></h5><p>A gallery of data visualizations made by Adam Pearce of Bloomberg Graphics.</p>
<h5><a href="http://www.smallmeans.com/new-york-times-infographics/" target="_blank">SmallMeans</a></h5><p>A gallery of favorited NYTimes graphics by a software engineering student.</p>
<h3>Data Visualization Blogs:</h3>
<h5><a href="http://flowingdata.com/" target="_blank">Flowing Data</a></h5><p>I suspect this is one of the most popular data visualization websites. It is the only one I have seen pop-up in my facebook feed several times</p>
<h5><a href="http://www.informationisbeautiful.net/" target="_blank">Information is Beautiful</a></h5><p>Run by David McCandless. This website has data visualization &#8220;best of&#8221; contests and lots of generally cool data visualizations.</p>
<h5><a href="http://feltron.com/">Nicholas Felton (website)</a></h5><p>More infographics than data visualizations, a big name worth checking out.</p><p><a href="http://feltron.tumblr.com/">Nicholar Felton (tumblr)</a></p><p>A curated selection put together by Felton. These are pieces of art as much as they are data visualizations.</p><p><a href="http://www.visualcinnamon.com/">Visual Cinnamon</a></p><p>Personal webpage of Nadieh Bremer who, in her own words, is a Astronomer-turned-Data-Scientist-turned-self-taught-Data-Visualization-Designer. In addition to her own work, which is stunning, she has a well curated list of internet resources and books on data visualization.</p><p><a href="http://fellinlovewithdata.com/" target="_blank">Fell In Love With Data</a></p><p>Not just pretty pictures, this blog has some excellent writing about what makes for good data visualizations. FILWD is edited by<a href="http://enrico.bertini.io/">Enrico Bertini</a>, Assistant Professor at the <a href="http://engineering.nyu.edu/">NYU Tandon School of Engineering</a>. He also has a podcast, <a href="http://datastori.es/">Data Stories</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/data-visualization-compilations/">Data Visualization Compilations</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/data-visualization-compilations/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">453</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Learning to Code</title>
		<link>/learning-to-code/</link>
		<comments>/learning-to-code/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2016 21:03:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[courses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CSS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HTML]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[javascript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Opinion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[python]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Iron Yard]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=325</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;A Highly Opinionated &#038; Abbreviated Guide for Taking the First Steps to Learn a Bit of Code&#8221; Why Write this?Someone asked me for help figuring out where to start regarding learning how to code today. Fundamentally, that&#8217;s why I&#8217;m writing this. I figured I&#8217;d might as well put it in a post and send her the link.Additionally,<a href="/learning-to-code/">[...]</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/learning-to-code/">Learning to Code</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<hr /><p><strong><em>&#8220;A Highly Opinionated & Abbreviated Guide for Taking the First Steps to Learn a Bit of Code&#8221;</em></strong></p>
<h3>Why Write this?</h3><p>Someone asked me for help figuring out where to start regarding learning how to code today. Fundamentally, that&#8217;s why I&#8217;m writing this. I figured I&#8217;d might as well put it in a post and send her the link.</p><p>Additionally, the results you get from googling &#8220;best ways to learn how to code&#8221; can be a bit daunting. They tend to be long lists of 10 to 50 different websites or books with only a short description about each. That&#8217;s not very useful. I know from personal experience figuring out how and where to start can lead to decision paralysis due to the large number of options.</p>
<h3>Warning!</h3><p>I&#8217;m still very much a newbie. Don&#8217;t put too much trust in anything I say. Some trust is okay, but let&#8217;s not go overboard.</p>
<h3>Who am I Writing for?</h3><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">My target audience is someone with no knowledge taking their first steps.</span> <strong>My goal is to help them avoid decision paralysis and simply start.</strong> Simply starting has a lot of value as it gets you to your first initial understanding of how exactly coding works and to the point where you can say, &#8220;I built that&#8221;. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Once you have a tiny bit of experience under your belt, it will be a lot easier to decide how much you like coding, easier to pick what you want to learn, and more obvious how you want to learn it.</span></p>
<h3>What am I Going to Cover?</h3><p><em>What language should you learn?</em></p>
<ul>
<li>I&#8217;m not going to describe the merits of every language. I&#8217;m going to focus on the most common languages and the easier languages to learn.</li>
</ul><p><em>How should you go about learning?</em></p>
<ul>
<li>I&#8217;m not going to give a big list of 30 or a 100 options for different websites and books to use. Google will give you lots of those. I&#8217;m going to describe the categories of different learning resources.</li>
</ul>
<h3>What Languages Should You Learn?</h3>
<h4>  If you want to build a website or put things on a website:</h4>
<ol>
<li>Sign up for a free web-builder like <a href="http://www.weebly.com/">Weebly</a>. Put something online quickly without coding knowledge to get some initial stoke.</li>
<li>Learn <a href="http://www.w3schools.com/html/default.asp" target="blank">HTML</a>, <a href="http://www.w3schools.com/css/default.asp" target="blank">CSS</a>, <a href="http://www.w3schools.com/js/default.asp" target="blank">JavaScript</a> &#8211; in that order. Use them to make a better website with your free web-builder.</li>
<li>Build simple web pages entirely from scratch without a web builder to hold your hand.</li>
<li>Learn the additional languages and libraries listed on <a href="http://www.w3schools.com/" target="blank">W3 schools</a>.</li>
</ol>
<h4>  If you want to work with data:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Python! Python is what a lot of scientists and academics use. It is also relatively easy to learn.</li>
<li>R is another good choice and very common in the social sciences.</li>
<li>Alternatively, if you&#8217;re interested in data visualization and not data analysis, then JavaScript.
<ul>
<li>To get inspired&#8230; Check out <a href="https://github.com/mbostock/d3/wiki/Gallery" target="blank">D3.js examples</a> for data visualization or <a href="http://leafletjs.com/examples.html" target="blank">leaflet.js </a>for map examples.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4>  If you want to make games:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Probably python.
<ul>
<li>Check out <a href="http://pygame.org/tags/example" target="blank">Pygame</a>.</li>
<li>Other languages are used in professional gaming, but python is a better place to start in terms of learning resources, ease of learning it, and lots of free example code you can reuse.</li>
<li>If you want to get very serious about games very quick, especially games with amazing graphics or in virtual reality, you might want to jump straight into Unity.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4>  If you want to use a computer language that runs inside another piece of software, likely at work:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Learn that language. It will  be faster to learn that language directly than learn another one and then switch. Get good at one before you diversify too much is repeated advice I see everywhere.</li>
</ul>
<h4> If you have no idea or have a small child to learn with you / help you when you get stuck:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://Code.org/" target="blank">Code.org</a>   Start learning code concepts by playing games (Star Wars!) and moving around instruction blocks. Build up to writing actual code in the JavaScript language.</li>
</ul>
<hr />
<hr />
<blockquote><p><em><span style="color: #993300;">For a longer and more visual version of this discussion, check out this awesome <a href="http://carlcheo.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/which-programming-language-should-i-learn-first-pdf.pdf" target="blank">infographic</a> for what language to learn at </span><a style="color: #993300;" href="http://carlcheo.com/" target="blank">carlcheo.com</a><span style="color: #993300;">. In addition to providing a flow-diagram for what deciding what language to learn, it describes common computer languages in terms of Lord of the Rings character traits. While you&#8217;re there, browse around a little. The site has powerfully communicative articles and infographics for newbies that explain a lot of things that get missed elsewhere. </span></em></p></blockquote>
<hr />
<hr /><p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3>What Are Your Options for Learning to Code?</h3><p>You have a huge variety of options. In fact, you probably have more options for learning code than most any subject out there. Instead of listing the websites and schools, I&#8217;m going to list the categories of different learning options. For some reason this approach is less common in google results.</p>
<h4>Conventional Educational Institution</h4>
<ul>
<li>CON = Takes a long time</li>
<li>CON = Expensive</li>
<li>PRO = Learn a lot of the theoretical computer science fundamentals.</li>
<li>PRO = Useful for getting a job</li>
<li>SUMMARY = <span style="text-decoration: underline; color: #008000;">Not what you should do if you&#8217;re just starting out as we assumed for this post.</span></li>
<li>EXAMPLE = Any four-year or two-year <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_academic_computer_science_departments">university</a> with a computer science department.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Code Boot Camp</h4>
<ul>
<li>CON = Expensive (thousands of dollars)</li>
<li>CON = As this is a relatively new concept, it is uncertain how it impacts your long-term job prospects.</li>
<li>CON = These are often start-ups and can have related growing pains and quality problems. Research!</li>
<li>PRO = Less time than conventional educational institutions</li>
<li>PRO = Cram a lot of information into your head in a relatively short amount of time.</li>
<li>PRO = Useful for getting a job</li>
<li>SUMMARY = <span style="text-decoration: underline; color: #008000;">Not what you should do if you&#8217;re just starting out as we assumed for this post.</span></li>
<li>EXAMPLE = <a href="https://www.theironyard.com/">The Iron Yard</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>MOOC = Massive Open Online Classes. (may or may not have certification & fixed schedule)</h4>
<ul>
<li>PRO = Learn from awesome professors in traditional lecture style without paying Harvard tuition.</li>
<li>PRO = Usually has additional resources not available in the website learning options below, like discussion boards, tests that are more than monkey-see monkey-do, and advanced final products to show off (see some of my early python posts)</li>
<li>PRO = Typically, you&#8217;ll be coding in the browser, which means you don&#8217;t have to worry about which version of python you have, how to set paths, or what the terminal is and how it differs from the PowerShell in Windows. This might not be true if the MOOC consists only of videos.</li>
<li>CON/PRO = Typically 4 &#8211; 12 weeks & 3-10 hours per week.</li>
<li>CON/PRO = If the class has fixed test and project deadlines, you can&#8217;t put it off for two weeks to deal with other stuff. On the other hand, deadlines make it more likely you&#8217;ll maintain forward momentum even if you have competing priorities. Some classes have deadlines with lots of tardy days to use up, which gives you best of both worlds.</li>
<li>CON/PRO = Means something on your resume, not a lot, but a little more with certification</li>
<li>SUMMARY = <span style="text-decoration: underline; color: #008000;">Can be great option if you like the traditional lecture learning methodology, want some personal interaction via discussion boards,</span> want at least a taste of computer science concepts, and are willing to commit to 3-8 hours a week for 5-12+ weeks. Whether or not it has a fixed schedule can be critical for whether it matches your needs.</li>
<li>EXAMPLE = <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/interactivepython1">An Introduction to Interactive Programming in Python</a>. By Rice Univ. C.S. dept. on Coursera.com or <a href="https://www.coursera.org/specializations/web-design">Learn to Design and Create Websites</a> by Univ. Michigan on Coursera.com</li>
</ul>
<h4>Free or Pay Website for Learning Code (may have little balloons that fall when you do good)</h4>
<ul>
<li>PRO = Short. Individual course segments can often be completed in a number of hours.</li>
<li>PRO = Typically, you&#8217;ll be coding in the browser, which means you don&#8217;t have to worry about which version of python you have, how to set paths, or what the terminal is and how it differs from the PowerShell in Windows.</li>
<li>PRO = Lots of silly things, great graphics, and quick immediate goals to keep you engaged and learning.</li>
<li>CON = Doesn&#8217;t really help your resume. May not teach you all you need to know, depending on your needs.</li>
<li>CON = No discussion board if you get stuck. Some have annoying mistakes in them.</li>
<li>SUMMARY = <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="color: #008000; text-decoration: underline;">If you like monkey see and monkey do learning</span></span> without in-depth discussion of concepts, this is perfect for you. If you want to <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="color: #008000; text-decoration: underline;">try out coding in a relatively short amount of time</span></span>, this is also good. If you want a more serious approach, maybe you skip this and go to one of the options above, or maybe you start here and quickly move to book or MOOC.</li>
<li>EXAMPLE: <a href="https://www.codecademy.com/">Codecademy.</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>Children&#8217;s Free Website for Learning Code</h4>
<ul>
<li>PRO/CON = Similar to above, but typically even less time to complete classes / segments.</li>
<li>SUMMARY = Purposely built to be short, fun, cute, and put you on a learning progression with lots of little steps. Good if you want to do this with your kid. <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="color: #008000; text-decoration: underline;">If you don&#8217;t know how interested you&#8217;ll be in coding and only want to spend &lt;2 hours to find out</span></span>, this is perhaps the option for you.</li>
<li>EXAMPLE: <a href="http://Code.org/">Code.org</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>Online Book or Physical Book</h4>
<ul>
<li>PRO = You get a nice book out of it. Reference manuals are very useful for coding. You now have one.</li>
<li>PRO = Step by step learning with a clear forward path to follow is very appealing for some people.</li>
<li>PRO = Work at your own pace. You can even skip ahead!</li>
<li>CON= You&#8217;ll likely have to download and install things. You&#8217;ll have to figure out how to use the terminal or command prompt to execute code and move files around. You&#8217;ll have to figure all this stuff out eventually, but, with learning out of a book, you have to figure it at the same time as you&#8217;re figuring out the coding part.</li>
<li>SUMMARY = I&#8217;m going to be opinionated and say I <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="color: #008000; text-decoration: underline;">don&#8217;t recommend just using a book as a learning method unless you  have some experience</span></span>. Too much installation and figuring out things in the terminal or command prompt before you actually get to learn what you want to learn. Go the book method in tandem with another option or after you&#8217;ve done another option.</li>
<li>EXAMPLE: <a href="http://learnpythonthehardway.org/book/">Learn Python The Hard Way</a>, by Zed Shaw or <a href="https://play.google.com/store/books/details?id=blCyf8XF41sC&source=productsearch&utm_source=HA_Desktop_US&utm_medium=SEM&utm_campaign=PLA&pcampaignid=MKTAD0930BO1&gl=US&gclid=CPnp7YXIncoCFdNpfgod3ooK_A&gclsrc=ds">HTML and CSS: Design and Build Websites</a> by John Puckett</li>
</ul>
<h4>Mentor + Any of the Above</h4>
<ul>
<li>PRO =  Mentors can help you figure out <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="color: #008000; text-decoration: underline;">how to address not knowing stuff</span></span>. How big a deal is not knowing something? What should you focus on learning? Why does this not work, and google won&#8217;t help me.</li>
<li>EXAMPLE = More experienced people on the internet or in person, experienced people at work, that other guy at the hackathon, people on stack overflow, computer science meet-ups, random coding boot camp alumni you email for more information, anyone who knows anything relevant that will drink beer or coffee with you, etc.</li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h3>How did I get started?</h3><p>My interest in coding resulted from my activities as a geologist. Although most of my time was spent on purpose-built software, sometimes I needed to do things that didn&#8217;t quite fit into standard software models or were annoyingly time intensive. I also ran up against memory limits in Excel on large datasets. Learning to code presented a way around these hurdles.</p><p>Once I put aside time for learning to write code in a more series manner, and not just editing example snippets run inside ArcGIS and other software packages, I found a set of classes taught by Rice Professors and offered online through Coursera to be very helpful. Course syllabi are available at this <a href="http://www.codeskulptor.org/coursera/interactivepython.html">link</a> and this <a href="http://www.codeskulptor.org/coursera/principlescomputing.html">link</a>. More general information about this sequence of python courses can be found <a href="https://www.coursera.org/specializations/fundamentalscomputing2">here</a>.</p><p>I took:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="headline-2-text">An Introduction to Interactive Programming in Python (Part 1) . <a href="https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/verify/9JJ2G6WVUA">Certificate</a> earned on April 10, 2015</p>
<p class="headline-2-text">An Introduction to Interactive Programming in Python (Part 2). <a href="https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/verify/Y5BQ7ZTRMD">Certificate</a> earned on May 14, 2015</p>
<p class="headline-2-text">Principles of Computing (Part 1) by Rice University on Coursera. <a href="https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/verify/XYXW9WQSXN">Certificate</a> earned on October 17, 2015</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<p class="headline-2-text">
<p class="headline-2-text"><b>Update</b>: Since I first wrote this, I&#8217;ve talked to many more people and been responsible for directing interns to learning resources. For people that want to spend a minimum amount of time to learn just a little, I&#8217;ve been directing them to resources that fall in the &#8220;Free or Pay Website for Learning Code&#8221; category. Additional learning resources that have worked well are:  <a href="https://code.org/">code.org</a> , <a href="http://w3schools.com/">w3schools.com</a> and <a href="https://www.codeschool.com/">codeschool.com</a> . Those options present a zero setup (everything can be run within their website) way to quickly dive-in.</p><p>&nbsp;</p><p>&nbsp;</p><p>&nbsp;</p><p>&nbsp;</p>
<hr /><p><em>Please feel free to leave any questions or comments via the comment box below!</em></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/learning-to-code/">Learning to Code</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Justin Gosses Home</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/learning-to-code/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">325</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
