<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>maps</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/maps/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Geology, Maps, and Code</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 04:15:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.4</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/cropped-JustinGosses_logo-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>maps</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Flow Chart for Picking the Right Mapping Tool</title>
		<link>/flow-chart-for-picking-the-right-mapping-tool/</link>
					<comments>/flow-chart-for-picking-the-right-mapping-tool/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2016 19:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ArcGIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CartoDB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data visualization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[draw.io]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[flowcharts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[javascript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Javascript library]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[leaflet.js]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mapbox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Map]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Mapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Opinion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[python]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://54.87.153.110/?p=732</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I did some research on different tools for creating flow charts today. Originally, I started down this path trying to figure out what open-source project I might be able to hack on and produce a project that would generate XKCD style flow charts, similar to how bokeh (python library) has XCKD<a class="moretag" href="/flow-chart-for-picking-the-right-mapping-tool/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I did some research on different tools for creating flow charts today.</p>
<p>Originally, I started down this path trying to figure out what open-source project I might be able to hack on and produce a project that would generate XKCD style flow charts, similar to how bokeh (python library) has XCKD style plots as built-in option. I was also playing around with the notion of crowd-sourced flow charts to help pick among tools and libraries as the number of options explode.</p>
<p>Then I got distracted and made the flow-chart below. I&#8217;ll just leave it here. It was made with <a href="http://draw.io/">draw.io</a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div id="wrapper" style="width: 100%; height: 100%; overflow: scroll !important; -webkit-overflow-scrolling: touch;">
<iframe loading="lazy" src="https://54.87.153.110/FlowChart_MakeMaps/" width="100%" height="1200px"></iframe>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/flow-chart-for-picking-the-right-mapping-tool/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Study for GIS Certification Exams</title>
		<link>/how-to-study-esri-gis-certification/</link>
					<comments>/how-to-study-esri-gis-certification/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2016 22:12:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ArcGIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ESRI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[python and GIS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://54.87.153.110/?p=416</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[GIS Certification: GIS certification is one of those certifications where no one is completely sure of its exact value. I don&#8217;t know of any business or organization where it is mandatory, but sometimes you see it listed under &#8220;preferred&#8221; on job advertisements. When I asked a question about the value of certification versus<a class="moretag" href="/how-to-study-esri-gis-certification/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>GIS Certification:</h3>
<p>GIS certification is one of those certifications where no one is completely sure of its exact value. I don&#8217;t know of any business or organization where it is mandatory, but sometimes you see it listed under &#8220;preferred&#8221; on job advertisements. When I asked <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/groups/3887350/3887350-6056100582890942467">a question about the value of certification versus portfolios</a> in a <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/groups/3887350">LinkedIN group devoted to GIS</a> (GIS and GEOGRAPHY), I got a range of responses, but generally few saw it as something with very significant value, more a nice to have.</p>
<h4>Why was I interested in Certification?</h4>
<p>Although I have experience with GIS, I never had GIS in my job title. Also, my previous work was all proprietary, so I couldn&#8217;t show anyone a portfolio of past work. Given these two limitations, I saw certification as a way to give myself more credibility.</p>
<p>The two most well known types of certification (at least in USA) are <a href="https://www.gisci.org/">GISP</a> and <a href="http://www.esri.com/training/main/certification">ESRI certification</a>. GISP is more of a longer process vs. simply taking a test, so I opted for the ESRI model.</p>
<h4>Don&#8217;t Sue Me</h4>
<p>Before and after taking an ESRI certification test, you are provided with strongly worded legal warnings to not discuss anything on the test with anyone ever. Therefore, I&#8217;m not going to talk about anything I learned from taking the test. I&#8217;m only going to discuss observations gleaned from ESRI supplied study material and my own experiences studying for one of their certification exams. These are concepts that maybe aren&#8217;t stressed in the ESRI study directions, but I believe to be useful. Certainly, I will use them if I take additional ESRI certification tests. Others might find them useful as well.</p>
<h3>Real World ArcGIS Use vs. Test Questions  &#8211;  Different Patterns:</h3>
<p>The ESRI certification tests are multiple choice. You do not use ArcGIS like a multiple choice test. This might seem a rather obvious observation. Perhaps it is, but it has value for understanding how you to study.</p>
<p>When I use ArcGIS or other ESRI product, I don&#8217;t necessarily remember the exact wording of buttons and menus. I remember where they are. I remember what they do. Maybe I remember something about what is written on a button or menu, but that memory is fuzzy. I may not remember the exact wording or phrasing. With the same task being accomplished on different programs by pushing buttons with very similar sounding names, there isn&#8217;t much reason to remember the exact name.</p>
<p>In contrast, in multiple choice questions asking what sequence of actions a user must follow to accomplish a specific GIS analysis, there is no spatial reference and exact phrasing matters. Hence, the information stored in your brain for how to do something in ArcGIS might not be stored in the same manner as it is asked in a multiple choice question.</p>
<p>This is a problem. <em><strong>If knowledge is stored in one semantic system and asked in another, you&#8217;re at risk of appearing less knowledgable</strong></em> than you actually are.</p>
<blockquote><p>Note: Perhaps there are people who work in ArcGIS as if it is a sequence of exact words to click? I don&#8217;t, but maybe those people exist? If that is you, this post doesn&#8217;t really apply. Sorry.</p></blockquote>
<h3>How I&#8217;m Going to Study for My Next GIS Certification Exam:</h3>
<p>Because of this difference in how my mind stores information required to do analysis in ArcGIS versus how questions are asked in a multiple choice test, <em><strong>I&#8217;m going to study in such a way to shift that knowledge out of spatial, visual, and procedure reference and into a sequence of exact words reference.</strong></em></p>
<p>In addition to the studying the ESRI supplied material, I will &#8230;</p>
<ol>
<li>Write down and remember the<strong><em> exact names</em></strong> <em>of button, menus, and options</em> found in the study material.</li>
<li>Write down and remember the order of buttons to do a task <strong>as a sequence of words independent of spatial position</strong>.</li>
<li>Note any <strong>differences</strong> in menu or button names <strong>between desktop and online applications</strong>.</li>
</ol>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3></h3>
<h3></h3>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-study-esri-gis-certification/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tableau Data Visualization Animal Control Calls</title>
		<link>/tableau-data-visualization/</link>
					<comments>/tableau-data-visualization/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2016 20:39:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CartoDB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mapbox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Map]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Mapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opendata]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tableau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://54.87.153.110/?p=364</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tableau: Data Visualization Software (&#38; mapping) Tableau is similar to CartoDB and MapBox, which were discussed in earlier posts here and here. All are designed to allow the user to quickly drop in data and create visual representations of that data. All have free and paid versions. Tableau Public is the<a class="moretag" href="/tableau-data-visualization/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Tableau: Data Visualization Software (&amp; mapping)</h3>
<p>Tableau is similar to <a href="https://cartodb.com/" target="blank">CartoDB</a> and <a href="https://www.mapbox.com/" target="blank">MapBox</a>, which were discussed in earlier posts <a href="https://54.87.153.110/cartodb-online-mapping/" target="blank">here</a> and <a href="https://54.87.153.110/using-mapbox-an-online-map-service/" target="blank">here</a>. All are designed to allow the user to quickly drop in data and create visual representations of that data. All have free and paid versions. <a href="https://public.tableau.com/s/" target="blank">Tableau Public</a> is the free version of Tableau. The main limitations for Tableau Public vs. the paid version is more limited range of input data types (you still get xls and csv) and projects can only be saved to your public gallery.</p>
<p>What sets Tableau apart is <strong><em>Tableau</em><em><strong> is</strong>n&#8217;t just maps. It attempts to cover data visualization in general. </em></strong>Bar charts, pie charts, scatter plots, etc. Think of anything you have ever seen come out of Excel, plus some things you haven&#8217;t. Maps are just one more type of data visualization for Tableau. Tableau also excels at moving very quickly from &#8220;I have structured data&#8221; to &#8220;I have multiple visualizations of that data sliced multiple ways. It allows interactive visualization for the end-user too.&#8221;</p>
<div></div>
<div>
<div id="attachment_397" style="width: 330px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png" target="blank"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-397" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-397" src="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png" alt="Screenshot of menu options for different default data visualization types." width="320" height="550" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png 320w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM-175x300.png 175w" sizes="(max-width: 320px) 100vw, 320px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-397" class="wp-caption-text">Screenshot of menu options for different default data visualization types.</p></div>
<h3 style="text-align: left;">Houston Data Visualization Meet-up</h3>
<p style="text-align: left;">This post was prompted by two talks at a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Houston-Data-Visualization-Meetup/events/227238782/">recent</a><a href="http://www.meetup.com/Houston-Data-Visualization-Meetup/" target="blank">Houston Data Visualization</a> Meet-up. I attend meet-ups on data visualization, JavaScript, and python to see new things and get an idea what other people are working on locally. This meet-up was hosted at <a href="https://txrxlabs.org/" target="blank">TXRX labs</a>, which is a cool space if you ever have an opportunity to go. To quote their &#8220;about us&#8221; section:</p>
<blockquote><p><em>Established in 2008, TXRX Labs is a non-profit hackerspace for the greater Houston area. Housed in the East End District, we offer courses in and access to our rapid prototyping lab, woodshop, machineshop, electronics lab, and a wide variety of other tools. Our goal is to educate the public about technology and show how seemingly complex techniques can be used by anyone.</em></p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">The two mains talks at the Data Visualization Meet-up were on Tableau and used real estate data. I won&#8217;t attempt to replicate them here, but I will include a link to Clay Cohoon&#8217;s <a href="https://public.tableau.com/profile/clay.cahoon#!/" target="blank">public gallery</a> of visualizations. Clay delivered an entertaining talk that walked the audience through Tableau from data loading to sharing the final product. There is also a lot of great stuff on <a href="https://public.tableau.com/s/gallery">Tableau&#8217;s gallery</a>, basically a greatest hits collection.</p>
<h4 style="text-align: left;">A static image of Clay&#8217;s Visualization Being Built in Tableau Public:</h4>
<p><a href="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-410 aligncenter" src="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png" alt="Image of Clay Cahoon's visualization dashboard from his talk." width="1360" height="768" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png 1360w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee-300x169.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee-1024x578.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1360px) 100vw, 1360px" /></a></p>
</div>
<div>
<h4 style="text-align: left;"><em>A few take away&#8217;s from Clay Cohoon&#8217;s talk were:</em></h4>
<ol>
<li style="text-align: left;">There&#8217;s <strong>a lot of interactivity baked into Tableau</strong> that allows the end-user to click a data point or label and have other maps or graphs in the dashboard automatically update to show only data for that label or datapoint.</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">By right clicking on a point or axis, the <strong>end-user can bring up an option to download a selected portion of the data</strong> to their own computer.</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">By including an option for calculated fields, Tableau allows you to do some <strong>data crunching right in Tableau, </strong>in addition the main purpose of data visualization. This <strong>saves time</strong> as you don&#8217;t have to go all the way back to start just to normalize your data using Excel.</li>
</ol>
</div>
<h3>My Tableau Project: Animal Control Calls in 77009 Zip Code 2012-2015</h3>
<p>As I needed data to throw into Tableau, I decided to check out <a href="http://data.ohouston.org/ target=">Houston&#8217;s Open Data </a>portal. Mostly because I was curious what the data would look like, I decided to use <a href="http://data.ohouston.org/dataset/barc-animal-service-requests" target="blank">BARC call data</a> from the 77009 zip code. <a href="http://www.houstontx.gov/barc/aboutbarc.html" target="blank">BARC</a> is Houston&#8217;s city-run animal shelter. They respond to animal control calls from the public.</p>
<p>My main insights after being able to look at the data visually were: a sizable portion of the calls to BARC are cancelled instead of completed, wild-animal calls make up a very small percentage of total calls, and, although calls are pretty evenly distributed, the most expensive portion of the Houston Heights (SW portion of 77009 zip code) had less calls on average.</p>
<h4><em>A few take aways from creating this visualization were:</em></h4>
<ol>
<li>The time it takes to go from opening Tableau to having your first visualization is very short. In the meet-up talks, it was approximately 15 minutes. In my first time using the program, it took me maybe an hour.</li>
<li>The user interface is intuitive enough that I stopped watching a tutorial video after a couple of minutes. I made my way through pressing buttons and experimenting without any aggravating moments.</li>
<li>Something that Clay Cahoon brought up during his talk, and that I noticed as well, is that although Tableau is super fast and easy to create first draft visualizations, adjusting the &#8220;fine details&#8221; like fonts and line widths is not nearly as quick. This is not a huge program, perhaps only surprising, given everything else is so intuitive and fast.</li>
</ol>
<p>As you explore the visualization below, CLICK ON THE DATA. If you click on a map data point, it brings up extra data. If you click on the bar graph, it affects what is shown in the map. All this interactivity is baked into Tablea. Zero clicks were needed to make it happen.</p>
<p>You can bring up a new full-window view by <strong>clicking <a href="https://public.tableau.com/profile/justin.gosses#!/vizhome/Houston77009Zipcode-CallstoAnimalControl/Dashboard_Small" target="blank">here</a></strong>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><embed src="https://public.tableau.com/shared/6K6WP2SGJ?:display_count=yes" width="1500" height="900"></embed></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/tableau-data-visualization/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ArcGIS Hackathon-ish</title>
		<link>/arcgis_hackathon/</link>
					<comments>/arcgis_hackathon/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 04:44:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ArcGIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ESRI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hackathon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[javascript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mobile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Mapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opendata]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[python and GIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://54.87.153.110/?p=265</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ESRI sponsored Geo-Development Hackathon: Today I took part in an event put on by ESRI, the company that provides the software on which the majority of enterprise,  academic, and government GIS work takes place. As compared to the Geophysics Hackathon run by AgileGeosciences at the Society of Exploration Geophysics Annual Conference, this<a class="moretag" href="/arcgis_hackathon/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>ESRI sponsored Geo-Development Hackathon:</h3>
<p>Today I took part in an event put on by <a href="http://www.esri.com/" target="blank">ESRI</a>, the company that provides the software on which the majority of enterprise,  academic, and government GIS work takes place. As compared to the <a href="https://54.87.153.110/geophysics-hackathon-at-2015-s-e-g-annual-meeting/" target="blank">Geophysics Hackathon</a> run by <a href="http://www.agilegeoscience.com/" target="blank">AgileGeosciences</a> at the Society of Exploration Geophysics Annual Conference, this was more about learning tools and less a crazy two day race. Hence, the title for this post is ArcGIS Hackathon-ish. There wasn&#8217;t any beer and pizza, but the cookies and cheese were good. Also, I got another free t-shirt. You can never have too many free t-shirts. The event was five hours long. Half was explanation and questions. The other half was building maps using the tools.</p>
<h4>The Tools</h4>
<p>The event focus was on a collection of tools accessed or associated with their ArcGIS developer <a href="https://developers.arcgis.com/en/" target="blank"><b>site</b></a>. ESRI staff provided a github <a href="https://github.com/ESRI/GEODEV-HACKERLABS" target="blank">repository</a> of links, instructions, and list of topics/tools to cover during the event or after. There were some useful step-by-step instructions included to get you started with several of the tools.</p>
<ul>
<li><b>Map Builder</b>: Load data &amp; edit basic symbology for first level, static maps you might embed in a website</li>
<li><b>App Builder</b>: Take a map you built from map builder and put it into a map application framework with lots of premade style, formatting, and widget options. A few example widgets are:
<ol>
<li>Turn layers off and on</li>
<li>Add query box to show selection subset of a layer</li>
<li>Show users&#8217; current location on the map</li>
<li>Allow a user to edit the map</li>
<li>Directions</li>
<li>Measurement (line, path, area)</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><b>ArcGIS API Javascript</b>: Javascript is one of the three key languages used in front-end web development (HTML and CSS being the other two). Javascript is the part that makes websites interactive. ArcGIS API javascript allows you to pull different basemaps, layers, etc. from your ArcGIS Online account, based on user interactions with the website, and display just the right map to the website user. You have to know javascript to do this, but the advantage is you can automatically deliver a map based on a large number of possible inputs. The opensource equivalent would leaflet.js.</li>
<li><b>Koop javascript</b>: Sometimes when you use open-source data, you get it in one file type and transform into appropriate file format before putting it in ArcGIS Online map. Koop.js is a version of javascript written to handle that data transformation for you automatically reducing some of the programming required. This might be particularly useful for dealing with realtime open-source data available on another website that you want to bring into your map. Apparently, it is new and still a little wobbly, but the presenter seemed very excited about it.</li>
<li><b>App Studio</b>: App Studio is basically App Builder, except you&#8217;re writing the javascript for a new template instead of relying on a drag and drop user interface. For now, this is free and even allows you to output native binaries, which means it outputs something that can go into the Android or Apple App store, without needing to deal with learning the Swift or Java language. People are putting the code they&#8217;re writing to build new apps and widgets in a ArcGIS marketplace and available opensource on GitHub.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Product From Those 5 Hours =</h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">A Map App On Holocene Volcanoes and Historical Major Earthquakes</h4>
<p>Click on the icons to bring up some of the map widgets and turn layers off and on. A full page version, which just looks nicer, can be found <b><a href="https://gosses.maps.arcgis.com/apps/webappviewer/index.html?id=b34ea4b002e1471488c060bb9a9200b7" target="blank">here.</a> </b></p>
<div class="embed-container"><iframe loading="lazy" title="Global Holocene Volcanism and Major Historical Earthquake Distribution" src="https://gosses.maps.arcgis.com/apps/webappviewer/index.html?id=b34ea4b002e1471488c060bb9a9200b7" width="1000" height="600"></iframe></div>
<h4 class="embed-container">Update: for those completely new to GIS</h4>
<p>You might not know that ArcGIS requires a license. If you don&#8217;t have access to a license through school or work, you can still get a free non-commercial <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/arcgis-for-desktop/free-trial" target="blank">trial license</a> for 60 days. There are also annual <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/arcgis-for-home" target="blank">ESRI</a> non-commercial licenses for $100.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/arcgis_hackathon/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Using Mapbox, an online map service</title>
		<link>/using-mapbox-an-online-map-service/</link>
					<comments>/using-mapbox-an-online-map-service/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 00:20:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ArcGIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[galveston]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[javascript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mapbox]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://54.87.153.110/?p=234</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What is Mapbox? Mapbox is an online map service, like CartoDB, which was discussed in a previous post. The value proposition of this type of services is you get to add a nice looking map to your webpage including the zoom and pan features users expect, without having to mess<a class="moretag" href="/using-mapbox-an-online-map-service/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>What is Mapbox?</h3>
<p>Mapbox is an online map service, like CartoDB, which was discussed in a previous post. The value proposition of this type of services is you get to add a nice looking map to your webpage including the zoom and pan features users expect, without having to mess with a full GIS program.</p>
<h5>First Impression Comparison to Other Options</h5>
<p>Compared to CartoDB, Mapbox seems to have a little bit more flexible and contains more features, which you can choose whether or not you use. It also has a javascript api similar to leaflet, which lets web or mobile developers create new maps on the fly based on user&#8217;s interactions within their own website. The additional options increase the level of fiddling around and exploring you end up doing, but don&#8217;t seem super distracting as Mapbox does a good job at keeping the extra options out of your way if you don&#8217;t want to use them.</p>
<h5>Favorite Feature</h5>
<p>I&#8217;ve not delved deep into every option yet, but one of my favorites was the ability to quickly change image characteristics like saturation, contrast, brightness, etc. The standard base maps imagery tends to be somewhat muted. There is good reasons for this. Often roads and layers that go over the basemap are what you want the users&#8217; eyes to go towards. With a geology background, however, there are times I want to see the variation of the natural features really pop. The map below is a good example of this. The original base map image provided didn&#8217;t show nearly as many interesting details, so I changed the image characteristics to bring out certain features.</p>
<h5>The Map Below</h5>
<p>The map below is a satellite image of Moody&#8217;s island in West Galveston bay. The area just to the west of this is sometimes called Christmas Bay. It is one of my favorite areas around Houston. The landscape around this area is in constant flux. Channels move. Sandy banks move. After a hurricane, the shoreline and houses built on it move. Variations in tides and river influx sometimes result in surprisingly clear water in which you can see jelly-fish, sting-rays, and hermit crabs.</p>
<p>The roofs are fishing shacks built on stilts. They can only be accessed by boat. The state doesn&#8217;t allow them to be built anymore, but they do allow the owners to maintain and use them following certain regulations.</p>
<p>The Houston area isn&#8217;t known for great outside recreation. Some people even assume there just isn&#8217;t any. To a certain extent they&#8217;re right, but then again there are lots of places like this with loads of wildlife and great scenery. They just take a shallow draft boat to get to, which isn&#8217;t that common. Plus, they&#8217;re not at all visible from the road, so, unlike mountains or canyons, people don&#8217;t necessary know they exist if they aren&#8217;t already out there.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="https://api.mapbox.com/styles/v1/jgosses/cii6llgu60000yglwxtzfikgm.html?title=true&amp;access_token=pk.eyJ1Ijoiamdvc3NlcyIsImEiOiJjaWk2aWhua2kwMWxidDBrZndhbHBraTd1In0.IIT7dwztvQhH9ZsiOLmnMg#16/29.077755149795877/-95.14694250103663/0" width="100%" height="800">nothing appearing in iframe</iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/using-mapbox-an-online-map-service/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CartoDB &#038; Online Mapping</title>
		<link>/cartodb-online-mapping/</link>
					<comments>/cartodb-online-mapping/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 01:43:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ArcGIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CartoDB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mobile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Mapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[outcrops]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[subsurface]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://54.87.153.110/?p=179</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Online Mapping: Recently, I&#8217;ve been improving my skills in both GIS, web development, and programming. As such, exploring online mapping services and methods, like leaflet, Mapbox and CartoDB, was on the &#8220;to do&#8221; list. Both CartoDB and Mapbox are sites that allow you to build maps on their webpage and then embed<a class="moretag" href="/cartodb-online-mapping/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>Online Mapping:</h4>
<p>Recently, I&#8217;ve been improving my skills in both GIS, web development, and programming. As such, exploring online mapping services and methods, like leaflet, Mapbox and CartoDB, was on the &#8220;to do&#8221; list. Both <a href="https://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a> and <a href="https://www.mapbox.com/">Mapbox</a> are sites that allow you to build maps on their webpage and then embed the maps in your webpage. <a href="http://leafletjs.com/">Leaflet</a> is a javascript library for interactive maps.</p>
<h4>Pro &amp; Con</h4>
<p>The main advantages of these services are; you don&#8217;t need to purchase a desktop GIS software, you don&#8217;t need to know how to use ArcGIS or QGIS, and they provide a variety of polished base maps. The main drawback is the functionality is more limited than a full desktop GIS software package. For some maps, this lack of functionality will be a deal breaker. For the map below, however, it wasn&#8217;t an issue. Not only that, but CartoDB allowed me to make the map faster than I would have been able to with ArcGIS. That being said, CartoDB could use better instructions. Their writing was a bit too sparse in places.</p>
<h4>Conclusion from my first map in CartoDB</h4>
<p>I think for quick maps, especially for maps that are largely points, a single path, or already created more complex layers overlaid on a base map, CartoDB is something I&#8217;ll continue to use. In a future post, I&#8217;ll try out MapBox and then Leaflet.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>&#8220;A Map of My Geology Experience&#8221; &#8211; built with CartDB</strong><br />
<iframe loading="lazy" src="https://jgosses82.cartodb.com/viz/a74cf9ea-8f1f-11e5-a802-0ecd1babdde5/embed_map" width="100%" height="520" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/cartodb-online-mapping/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#8220;Get Current Address&#8221; python script on phone</title>
		<link>/get-current-address-python-script-on-phone/</link>
					<comments>/get-current-address-python-script-on-phone/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2015 20:23:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[courses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mobile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[python and GIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pythonista]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://54.87.153.110/?p=141</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#8220;Get Current Address&#8221; A Pythonista Script running on iPhone: &#8220;Get Current Address&#8221; is a pythonista script I created based on some google research. I wanted to take advantage of the iphone&#8217;s geolocation and geocoding abilities. I was also attempting to fill a very small niche. Although google maps and apple maps<a class="moretag" href="/get-current-address-python-script-on-phone/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>&#8220;Get Current Address&#8221;</h3>
<h4>A Pythonista Script running on iPhone:</h4>
<p>&#8220;Get Current Address&#8221; is a <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/pythonista/id528579881?mt=8 target=">pythonista</a> script I created based on some google research. I wanted to take advantage of the iphone&#8217;s geolocation and geocoding abilities.</p>
<p>I was also attempting to fill a very small niche. Although google maps and apple maps are good at showing where you are and where a certain address is, there is no built in functionality to quickly show you the address at which you and your phone are currently positioned within.</p>
<p>It can also output course direction and speed when the phone is moving.</p>
<div id="attachment_142" style="width: 462px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><a href="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/GetAddress.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-142" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-142" src="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/GetAddress.png" alt="Screen shot of pythonista screen showing results of &quot;Get Location&quot; script." width="452" height="425" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/GetAddress.png 452w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/11/GetAddress-300x282.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 452px) 100vw, 452px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-142" class="wp-caption-text">Screen shot of pythonista screen showing results of &#8220;Get Location&#8221; script.</p></div>
<p>You can check out the code on github: <a href="https://github.com/JustinGOSSES/Pythonista" target="blank"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-224" src="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/GitHub-Mark-32px.png" alt="GitHub-Mark-32px" width="32" height="32" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/get-current-address-python-script-on-phone/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Map of Houston Paddling Experiences: Post 1</title>
		<link>/map-of-houston-area-paddling-experiences-post-1/</link>
					<comments>/map-of-houston-area-paddling-experiences-post-1/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 18:41:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ArcGIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[KayakMap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opendata]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[San Jacinto River]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spring Creek]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://54.87.153.110/?p=60</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One of the maps I am currently building is an attempt at a different style of map for kayaking and canoeing in the greater Houston &#8211; Galveston area.  Instead of focusing on getting to the put-in location and where to start and stop on the water, I wanted to convey<a class="moretag" href="/map-of-houston-area-paddling-experiences-post-1/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the maps I am currently building is an attempt at a different style of map for kayaking and canoeing in the greater Houston &#8211; Galveston area.  Instead of focusing on getting to the put-in location and where to start and stop on the water, I wanted to convey more information about what type of paddling experience could be had via map details.</p>
<p>This type of information, on the paddlers experiences, is usually kept within text and photos that must be scrolled through, making it slow for the user to gain a perspective on what types of paddling trips are available in the area.</p>
<p>An abstract that I&#8217;ve submitted to the 2016 ArcGIS user conference in San Diego based on this map is below.</p>
<p>Abstract:</p>
<blockquote><p>Paddling recreation maps often focus on navigation. They consist of access points and known travel paths. An alternative is to map spatial variation of the characteristics that make up the paddling experience, information traditionally found only in text and images. Characteristics like natural or built shoreline, enclosed or panoramic views, forested versus grassy banks, types of wildlife sightings, etc. can all be mapped using public datasets and GIS to create a new type of paddling map.</p></blockquote>
<p>The plan is to publish a series of posts charting the process of building the map. This is the first post.</p>
<p>Below is a peak at early work: Green is forested areas, pink is urban, and gray is grassy areas. The larger river is San Jacinto River. The smaller is Spring Creek. The red lines are route 59. The shading is topography from a digital elevation model built from lidar data.</p>
<p><a href="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/KayakMap_Peak_1.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-61" src="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/KayakMap_Peak_1.png" alt="KayakMap_Peak_1" width="457" height="632" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/KayakMap_Peak_1.png 457w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/11/KayakMap_Peak_1-217x300.png 217w" sizes="(max-width: 457px) 100vw, 457px" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/map-of-houston-area-paddling-experiences-post-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
