<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>opendata</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/opendata/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Geology, Maps, and Code</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 04:34:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.4</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/cropped-JustinGosses_logo-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>opendata</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Game of Thrones Parallel Sets Data Visualization</title>
		<link>/game-of-thrones-parallel-sets-data-visualization/</link>
					<comments>/game-of-thrones-parallel-sets-data-visualization/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2016 18:31:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[d3]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[d3.js]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data visualization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Front-End]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Game of Thrones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[javascript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opendata]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://54.87.153.110/?p=748</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[User interface add-ons to make a better parallel sets visualizations: (skip to the data visualization here.) Parallel sets is a data visualization type that shows how attributes of different types are distributed across a large number of instances. Common examples include datasets of the characteristics of passengers on the Titanic disaster and nutrition<a class="moretag" href="/game-of-thrones-parallel-sets-data-visualization/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>User interface add-ons to make a better parallel sets visualizations:</h2>
<p style="text-align: center;">(skip to the data visualization <a href="https://54.87.153.110/ParaSet_Oct2/" target="_blank">here</a>.)</p>
<p>Parallel sets is a data visualization type that shows how attributes of different types are distributed across a large number of instances. Common examples include datasets of the characteristics of passengers on the Titanic disaster and nutrition information of many different types of cereal. Parallel sets data visualizations are good at showing how attributes do or don&#8217;t cluster over a large dataset of instances. It is a data visualization type favored when the data is categorical and not strictly numerical.</p>
<p>I built a <a href="https://54.87.153.110/parallel-sets-data-visualization/">parallel sets data visualization</a> based on a dataset of battles from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Game_of_Thrones">Game of Thrones series</a> (TV version, not book). Examples questions that can be answered by a <a href="https://54.87.153.110/ParaSet_Oct2/" target="_blank">parallel sets</a> built from this data include: Which battle type has the best success rate? Which house has the best and track record in terms of number of battles won or lost? Were there more pitched battles versus ambushes in later years versus earlier years? Are battles in certain regions more likely to result in a major characters death?</p>
<p>The parallel sets visualizations that I&#8217;ve seen work best when the number of types of attributes is between 3 and 10, the number of different attributes within each type is &lt;10, and the total number of instances is &gt;100.  Outside this range, parallel sets tend to get too cluttered.</p>
<p>When I used parallel sets for a project at work, I found it be successful for the immediate problem but very easy to be cluttered and messy if I tried to include all characteristics found in the dataset. Although a subset of the data was fine for showing what I was interested in at the time, I knew eventually I would want to show a larger dataset and let the user explore the data. This led to brainstorming potential improvements for my initial parallel sets code base, which I had adopted from Jason Davis <a href="https://github.com/jasondavies/d3-parsets" target="_blank">parasets </a>project. Both us d3.js. <span style="color: #333399;">I&#8217;ve completed the first two interactivity improvements listed below in this</span> <a href="https://54.87.153.110/ParaSet_Oct2/" target="_blank">visualization</a>.</p>
<ol>
<li><span style="color: #333399;">User can select which data dimensions to visualize (types of attributes: region, year, defender, etc.)</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #333399;">User can limit the visualization to only data that contains a certain value in a certain dimension (battles with Stark as the defender)</span></li>
<li>User can chose to turn numerical information into small categorical groups (size of battle was &gt; or &lt; some number)<br />
a. user selects n number of divisions of the data between min and max<br />
b. or n number of divisions based on equal number in each category<br />
c. or by log divisions (&gt;10, &gt;100, &gt;1000, etc.)</li>
<li>Interactive combination of histogram and parallel sets data visualizations via dc.js.</li>
<li>Pre-determined combinations of data dimensions available via a series of buttons to assist in story-telling to user.</li>
</ol>
<p>Letting the user select the input data and try different combinations reduces cluttering. Giving the user the option to pick the input data makes this data visualization more of a data exploration tool and less of a straight forward story telling image.</p>
<p>It is also useful if you don&#8217;t have HBO but want to study up for water cooler conversations.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3>Examples from the Game of Thrones Parallel Sets Visualization:</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>ribbon width = number of battles</em></p>
<div id="attachment_750" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.29.28-PM.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-750" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-750 size-large" src="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.29.28-PM-1024x713.png" alt="Battles Type Vs. Outcome" width="640" height="446" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.29.28-PM-1024x713.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.29.28-PM-300x209.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.29.28-PM.png 2006w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-750" class="wp-caption-text">Battles Type Vs. Outcome</p></div>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Ambushes, razing, and siege perform better for the attacker than a pitched battle. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_751" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.36.24-PM.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-751" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-751 size-large" src="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.36.24-PM-1024x632.png" alt="Who loses battles vs. wins battles." width="640" height="395" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.36.24-PM-1024x632.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.36.24-PM-300x185.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.36.24-PM.png 1988w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-751" class="wp-caption-text">Who loses battles vs. wins battles.</p></div>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Freefolk (black ribbon) have a horrible track record at attacking. House Stark and Baratheon are also not that great.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_752" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.37.40-PM.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-752" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-752 size-large" src="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.37.40-PM-1024x644.png" alt="Battles vs. character deaths" width="640" height="403" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.37.40-PM-1024x644.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.37.40-PM-300x189.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-12.37.40-PM.png 1964w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-752" class="wp-caption-text">Battles vs. character deaths: 1 = major character death, 0 = no major character death</p></div>
<p><em>Lannister, Stark, and Baratheon have the highest number of battles where they are the main attacker and an important character dies. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_754" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-1.24.35-PM.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-754" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-754 size-large" src="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-1.24.35-PM-1024x637.png" alt="Who wins when defending and major character deaths" width="640" height="398" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-1.24.35-PM-1024x637.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-1.24.35-PM-300x187.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Screen-Shot-2016-10-10-at-1.24.35-PM.png 1964w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-754" class="wp-caption-text">Who wins when defending and major character deaths</p></div>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>The attacker usually wins in a Game of Thrones battle, but when they lose, it tends to be when the main defender is a Lannister. In those battles where a defending Lannister wins, it is also common for a major character of some type to die. </em></p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;">Explore the live data visualization <a href="https://54.87.153.110/ParaSet_Oct2/" target="_blank">here</a>.</h2>
<h2></h2>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/game-of-thrones-parallel-sets-data-visualization/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tableau Data Visualization Animal Control Calls</title>
		<link>/tableau-data-visualization/</link>
					<comments>/tableau-data-visualization/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2016 20:39:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CartoDB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mapbox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Map]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Mapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opendata]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tableau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://54.87.153.110/?p=364</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tableau: Data Visualization Software (&#38; mapping) Tableau is similar to CartoDB and MapBox, which were discussed in earlier posts here and here. All are designed to allow the user to quickly drop in data and create visual representations of that data. All have free and paid versions. Tableau Public is the<a class="moretag" href="/tableau-data-visualization/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Tableau: Data Visualization Software (&amp; mapping)</h3>
<p>Tableau is similar to <a href="https://cartodb.com/" target="blank">CartoDB</a> and <a href="https://www.mapbox.com/" target="blank">MapBox</a>, which were discussed in earlier posts <a href="https://54.87.153.110/cartodb-online-mapping/" target="blank">here</a> and <a href="https://54.87.153.110/using-mapbox-an-online-map-service/" target="blank">here</a>. All are designed to allow the user to quickly drop in data and create visual representations of that data. All have free and paid versions. <a href="https://public.tableau.com/s/" target="blank">Tableau Public</a> is the free version of Tableau. The main limitations for Tableau Public vs. the paid version is more limited range of input data types (you still get xls and csv) and projects can only be saved to your public gallery.</p>
<p>What sets Tableau apart is <strong><em>Tableau</em><em><strong> is</strong>n&#8217;t just maps. It attempts to cover data visualization in general. </em></strong>Bar charts, pie charts, scatter plots, etc. Think of anything you have ever seen come out of Excel, plus some things you haven&#8217;t. Maps are just one more type of data visualization for Tableau. Tableau also excels at moving very quickly from &#8220;I have structured data&#8221; to &#8220;I have multiple visualizations of that data sliced multiple ways. It allows interactive visualization for the end-user too.&#8221;</p>
<div></div>
<div>
<div id="attachment_397" style="width: 330px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png" target="blank"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-397" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-397" src="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png" alt="Screenshot of menu options for different default data visualization types." width="320" height="550" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM.png 320w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Screen-Shot-2016-01-12-at-2.56.18-PM-175x300.png 175w" sizes="(max-width: 320px) 100vw, 320px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-397" class="wp-caption-text">Screenshot of menu options for different default data visualization types.</p></div>
<h3 style="text-align: left;">Houston Data Visualization Meet-up</h3>
<p style="text-align: left;">This post was prompted by two talks at a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Houston-Data-Visualization-Meetup/events/227238782/">recent</a><a href="http://www.meetup.com/Houston-Data-Visualization-Meetup/" target="blank">Houston Data Visualization</a> Meet-up. I attend meet-ups on data visualization, JavaScript, and python to see new things and get an idea what other people are working on locally. This meet-up was hosted at <a href="https://txrxlabs.org/" target="blank">TXRX labs</a>, which is a cool space if you ever have an opportunity to go. To quote their &#8220;about us&#8221; section:</p>
<blockquote><p><em>Established in 2008, TXRX Labs is a non-profit hackerspace for the greater Houston area. Housed in the East End District, we offer courses in and access to our rapid prototyping lab, woodshop, machineshop, electronics lab, and a wide variety of other tools. Our goal is to educate the public about technology and show how seemingly complex techniques can be used by anyone.</em></p></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">The two mains talks at the Data Visualization Meet-up were on Tableau and used real estate data. I won&#8217;t attempt to replicate them here, but I will include a link to Clay Cohoon&#8217;s <a href="https://public.tableau.com/profile/clay.cahoon#!/" target="blank">public gallery</a> of visualizations. Clay delivered an entertaining talk that walked the audience through Tableau from data loading to sharing the final product. There is also a lot of great stuff on <a href="https://public.tableau.com/s/gallery">Tableau&#8217;s gallery</a>, basically a greatest hits collection.</p>
<h4 style="text-align: left;">A static image of Clay&#8217;s Visualization Being Built in Tableau Public:</h4>
<p><a href="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-410 aligncenter" src="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png" alt="Image of Clay Cahoon's visualization dashboard from his talk." width="1360" height="768" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee.png 1360w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee-300x169.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Trustee-1024x578.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1360px) 100vw, 1360px" /></a></p>
</div>
<div>
<h4 style="text-align: left;"><em>A few take away&#8217;s from Clay Cohoon&#8217;s talk were:</em></h4>
<ol>
<li style="text-align: left;">There&#8217;s <strong>a lot of interactivity baked into Tableau</strong> that allows the end-user to click a data point or label and have other maps or graphs in the dashboard automatically update to show only data for that label or datapoint.</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">By right clicking on a point or axis, the <strong>end-user can bring up an option to download a selected portion of the data</strong> to their own computer.</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">By including an option for calculated fields, Tableau allows you to do some <strong>data crunching right in Tableau, </strong>in addition the main purpose of data visualization. This <strong>saves time</strong> as you don&#8217;t have to go all the way back to start just to normalize your data using Excel.</li>
</ol>
</div>
<h3>My Tableau Project: Animal Control Calls in 77009 Zip Code 2012-2015</h3>
<p>As I needed data to throw into Tableau, I decided to check out <a href="http://data.ohouston.org/ target=">Houston&#8217;s Open Data </a>portal. Mostly because I was curious what the data would look like, I decided to use <a href="http://data.ohouston.org/dataset/barc-animal-service-requests" target="blank">BARC call data</a> from the 77009 zip code. <a href="http://www.houstontx.gov/barc/aboutbarc.html" target="blank">BARC</a> is Houston&#8217;s city-run animal shelter. They respond to animal control calls from the public.</p>
<p>My main insights after being able to look at the data visually were: a sizable portion of the calls to BARC are cancelled instead of completed, wild-animal calls make up a very small percentage of total calls, and, although calls are pretty evenly distributed, the most expensive portion of the Houston Heights (SW portion of 77009 zip code) had less calls on average.</p>
<h4><em>A few take aways from creating this visualization were:</em></h4>
<ol>
<li>The time it takes to go from opening Tableau to having your first visualization is very short. In the meet-up talks, it was approximately 15 minutes. In my first time using the program, it took me maybe an hour.</li>
<li>The user interface is intuitive enough that I stopped watching a tutorial video after a couple of minutes. I made my way through pressing buttons and experimenting without any aggravating moments.</li>
<li>Something that Clay Cahoon brought up during his talk, and that I noticed as well, is that although Tableau is super fast and easy to create first draft visualizations, adjusting the &#8220;fine details&#8221; like fonts and line widths is not nearly as quick. This is not a huge program, perhaps only surprising, given everything else is so intuitive and fast.</li>
</ol>
<p>As you explore the visualization below, CLICK ON THE DATA. If you click on a map data point, it brings up extra data. If you click on the bar graph, it affects what is shown in the map. All this interactivity is baked into Tablea. Zero clicks were needed to make it happen.</p>
<p>You can bring up a new full-window view by <strong>clicking <a href="https://public.tableau.com/profile/justin.gosses#!/vizhome/Houston77009Zipcode-CallstoAnimalControl/Dashboard_Small" target="blank">here</a></strong>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><embed src="https://public.tableau.com/shared/6K6WP2SGJ?:display_count=yes" width="1500" height="900"></embed></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/tableau-data-visualization/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ArcGIS Hackathon-ish</title>
		<link>/arcgis_hackathon/</link>
					<comments>/arcgis_hackathon/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 04:44:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ArcGIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ESRI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hackathon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[javascript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mobile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online Mapping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opendata]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[python and GIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://54.87.153.110/?p=265</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ESRI sponsored Geo-Development Hackathon: Today I took part in an event put on by ESRI, the company that provides the software on which the majority of enterprise,  academic, and government GIS work takes place. As compared to the Geophysics Hackathon run by AgileGeosciences at the Society of Exploration Geophysics Annual Conference, this<a class="moretag" href="/arcgis_hackathon/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>ESRI sponsored Geo-Development Hackathon:</h3>
<p>Today I took part in an event put on by <a href="http://www.esri.com/" target="blank">ESRI</a>, the company that provides the software on which the majority of enterprise,  academic, and government GIS work takes place. As compared to the <a href="https://54.87.153.110/geophysics-hackathon-at-2015-s-e-g-annual-meeting/" target="blank">Geophysics Hackathon</a> run by <a href="http://www.agilegeoscience.com/" target="blank">AgileGeosciences</a> at the Society of Exploration Geophysics Annual Conference, this was more about learning tools and less a crazy two day race. Hence, the title for this post is ArcGIS Hackathon-ish. There wasn&#8217;t any beer and pizza, but the cookies and cheese were good. Also, I got another free t-shirt. You can never have too many free t-shirts. The event was five hours long. Half was explanation and questions. The other half was building maps using the tools.</p>
<h4>The Tools</h4>
<p>The event focus was on a collection of tools accessed or associated with their ArcGIS developer <a href="https://developers.arcgis.com/en/" target="blank"><b>site</b></a>. ESRI staff provided a github <a href="https://github.com/ESRI/GEODEV-HACKERLABS" target="blank">repository</a> of links, instructions, and list of topics/tools to cover during the event or after. There were some useful step-by-step instructions included to get you started with several of the tools.</p>
<ul>
<li><b>Map Builder</b>: Load data &amp; edit basic symbology for first level, static maps you might embed in a website</li>
<li><b>App Builder</b>: Take a map you built from map builder and put it into a map application framework with lots of premade style, formatting, and widget options. A few example widgets are:
<ol>
<li>Turn layers off and on</li>
<li>Add query box to show selection subset of a layer</li>
<li>Show users&#8217; current location on the map</li>
<li>Allow a user to edit the map</li>
<li>Directions</li>
<li>Measurement (line, path, area)</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><b>ArcGIS API Javascript</b>: Javascript is one of the three key languages used in front-end web development (HTML and CSS being the other two). Javascript is the part that makes websites interactive. ArcGIS API javascript allows you to pull different basemaps, layers, etc. from your ArcGIS Online account, based on user interactions with the website, and display just the right map to the website user. You have to know javascript to do this, but the advantage is you can automatically deliver a map based on a large number of possible inputs. The opensource equivalent would leaflet.js.</li>
<li><b>Koop javascript</b>: Sometimes when you use open-source data, you get it in one file type and transform into appropriate file format before putting it in ArcGIS Online map. Koop.js is a version of javascript written to handle that data transformation for you automatically reducing some of the programming required. This might be particularly useful for dealing with realtime open-source data available on another website that you want to bring into your map. Apparently, it is new and still a little wobbly, but the presenter seemed very excited about it.</li>
<li><b>App Studio</b>: App Studio is basically App Builder, except you&#8217;re writing the javascript for a new template instead of relying on a drag and drop user interface. For now, this is free and even allows you to output native binaries, which means it outputs something that can go into the Android or Apple App store, without needing to deal with learning the Swift or Java language. People are putting the code they&#8217;re writing to build new apps and widgets in a ArcGIS marketplace and available opensource on GitHub.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Product From Those 5 Hours =</h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">A Map App On Holocene Volcanoes and Historical Major Earthquakes</h4>
<p>Click on the icons to bring up some of the map widgets and turn layers off and on. A full page version, which just looks nicer, can be found <b><a href="https://gosses.maps.arcgis.com/apps/webappviewer/index.html?id=b34ea4b002e1471488c060bb9a9200b7" target="blank">here.</a> </b></p>
<div class="embed-container"><iframe loading="lazy" title="Global Holocene Volcanism and Major Historical Earthquake Distribution" src="https://gosses.maps.arcgis.com/apps/webappviewer/index.html?id=b34ea4b002e1471488c060bb9a9200b7" width="1000" height="600"></iframe></div>
<h4 class="embed-container">Update: for those completely new to GIS</h4>
<p>You might not know that ArcGIS requires a license. If you don&#8217;t have access to a license through school or work, you can still get a free non-commercial <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/arcgis-for-desktop/free-trial" target="blank">trial license</a> for 60 days. There are also annual <a href="http://www.esri.com/software/arcgis/arcgis-for-home" target="blank">ESRI</a> non-commercial licenses for $100.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/arcgis_hackathon/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Map of Houston Paddling Experiences: Post 1</title>
		<link>/map-of-houston-area-paddling-experiences-post-1/</link>
					<comments>/map-of-houston-area-paddling-experiences-post-1/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Justin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 18:41:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ArcGIS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[KayakMap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opendata]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[San Jacinto River]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spring Creek]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://54.87.153.110/?p=60</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One of the maps I am currently building is an attempt at a different style of map for kayaking and canoeing in the greater Houston &#8211; Galveston area.  Instead of focusing on getting to the put-in location and where to start and stop on the water, I wanted to convey<a class="moretag" href="/map-of-houston-area-paddling-experiences-post-1/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the maps I am currently building is an attempt at a different style of map for kayaking and canoeing in the greater Houston &#8211; Galveston area.  Instead of focusing on getting to the put-in location and where to start and stop on the water, I wanted to convey more information about what type of paddling experience could be had via map details.</p>
<p>This type of information, on the paddlers experiences, is usually kept within text and photos that must be scrolled through, making it slow for the user to gain a perspective on what types of paddling trips are available in the area.</p>
<p>An abstract that I&#8217;ve submitted to the 2016 ArcGIS user conference in San Diego based on this map is below.</p>
<p>Abstract:</p>
<blockquote><p>Paddling recreation maps often focus on navigation. They consist of access points and known travel paths. An alternative is to map spatial variation of the characteristics that make up the paddling experience, information traditionally found only in text and images. Characteristics like natural or built shoreline, enclosed or panoramic views, forested versus grassy banks, types of wildlife sightings, etc. can all be mapped using public datasets and GIS to create a new type of paddling map.</p></blockquote>
<p>The plan is to publish a series of posts charting the process of building the map. This is the first post.</p>
<p>Below is a peak at early work: Green is forested areas, pink is urban, and gray is grassy areas. The larger river is San Jacinto River. The smaller is Spring Creek. The red lines are route 59. The shading is topography from a digital elevation model built from lidar data.</p>
<p><a href="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/KayakMap_Peak_1.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-61" src="http://54.87.153.110/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/KayakMap_Peak_1.png" alt="KayakMap_Peak_1" width="457" height="632" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/KayakMap_Peak_1.png 457w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/11/KayakMap_Peak_1-217x300.png 217w" sizes="(max-width: 457px) 100vw, 457px" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/map-of-houston-area-paddling-experiences-post-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
